<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - anthropology</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/anthropology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T13:22:46+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Oscar Krüger article: What's in a container?</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/oscar-kruger-article-whats-in-a-container.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2023-06-01:/oscar-kruger-article-whats-in-a-container.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are all consumers of many kinds of goods, and in that capacity, we
can hardly be unaware of the importance of the containers in which those
goods are packaged. Containers protect and condition what they contain,
and they can be part of the experience of consumption, enhancing or
limiting …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are all consumers of many kinds of goods, and in that capacity, we
can hardly be unaware of the importance of the containers in which those
goods are packaged. Containers protect and condition what they contain,
and they can be part of the experience of consumption, enhancing or
limiting our enjoyment of the good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are less accustomed to thinking about the role of containers in
the process of production. I read a fascinating ethnographic article
recently that draws attention to just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oscar Krüger, a social anthropologist at Lund University, spent
several years researching small wine production in Italy (I was
fortunate to be able to contribute to the supervision of his PhD on the
topic). In ‘Peasant in a Bottle: Infrastructures of Containment for an
Italian Wine Cooperative’, published in &lt;em&gt;Ethnos&lt;/em&gt;, he explains the
importance of different kinds of containers of wine for artisinal
producers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard designs of the glass wine bottle were established long
ago. There are only a few options, and any elaboration is taken to be
flashy, rather than as a sign of quality. But that doesn’t mean that the
bottle is unimportant for the producer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the wine producers’ point of view, there are two ways of selling
wine into the consumer market, distinguished by the type of container
used. Most wine is sold to wholesalers in tanks, to be blended and
bottled later on, close to the end market. Bottling at the site of
production is more expensive, but is a seal of quality. That is because
it allows what is distinctive about the product–above all its expression
of a specific &lt;em&gt;terroir&lt;/em&gt;–to be preserved from the vinyard to the
table. As Oscar writes, ‘by integrating the act of sealing into the
grape-growing farm itself, the winemakers ensure that they themselves
are made present at that final point, irrespective of whether it is
Turin or Tokyo’ (p.9). The bottle remains sealed until it is opened by
the consumer, whereas wine sold in tanks will be decanted into a series
of different containers before it is bottled, breaking the connection
with the specific site of production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This connection between the glass bottle and the marketable quality
of the character of the wine of a single estate goes back to the 1660s,
where the idea of &lt;em&gt;terroir&lt;/em&gt; as the expression of the unchanging
and unique ‘taste of the place’ developed early. The extension of this
idea in Italy, as &lt;em&gt;territorialitá&lt;/em&gt;, has been seen as a way to
escape the downward pressure on prices that has come with the
development of commodity markets in food and drinks. Tying a specific
product–first wine, then a host of other comestible products–to a
specific place allows both product and place to acquire greater
distinctiveness and greater value. Clearly where this connection is
facilitated by the relatively small and heavy glass bottle, it comes at
a cost for the producer, and for the environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="business"></category><category term="consumption"></category><category term="production"></category><category term="wine"></category><category term="ethnography"></category></entry><entry><title>Post-truth anthropology—published in Anthropology Today</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/post-truth-anthropology-published-in-anthropology-today.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2017-06-02:/post-truth-anthropology-published-in-anthropology-today.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1467-8322.12346/abstract?campaign=woletoc"&gt;guest
editorial on ‘Post-truth anthropology’&lt;/a&gt; that I wrote for
&lt;em&gt;Anthropology Today&lt;/em&gt; is out today. &lt;del&gt;It’s paywalled, I’m happy
to send the text on request if you can’t access it.&lt;/del&gt; Edit: it has
now been made open access for a period of 6 months — if it’s …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1467-8322.12346/abstract?campaign=woletoc"&gt;guest
editorial on ‘Post-truth anthropology’&lt;/a&gt; that I wrote for
&lt;em&gt;Anthropology Today&lt;/em&gt; is out today. &lt;del&gt;It’s paywalled, I’m happy
to send the text on request if you can’t access it.&lt;/del&gt; Edit: it has
now been made open access for a period of 6 months — if it’s paywalled
again by the time you read this and you can’t access it but want a copy,
comment on this post and I’ll send it to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Countless commentators have announced the advent of the post-truth
era, but while everyone seems to be talking about it, there is little
agreement about what it really means. This article argues that
anthropology can make an important and distinctive contribution to
understanding post-truth by treating it ethnographically. Commonly
proposed explanations for post-truth include changes in political
culture, in the structure of information in the digital age and
universal cognitive weaknesses that limit people’s capacity for critical
thought. While all these are likely important factors, they do not
account for the role of culture in creating and sustaining post-truth.
In fact, it is likely that culture, especially in the form of
metacognition, or thought about thought, plays an important role by
providing knowledge practices, techniques for allocating attention, and
especially competing theories of truth. Ethnographic methods provide
anthropologists with a distinctive window on post-truth cultures of
metacognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1467-8322.12346/abstract?campaign=woletoc"&gt;Post-truth
anthropology – Mair – 2017 – Anthropology Today&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology today"></category><category term="ignorance"></category><category term="post-truth anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="metacognition"></category><category term="post-truth"></category></entry><entry><title>Schumacher’s ‘Buddhist economics’</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/schumachers-buddhist-economics.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-04-04T23:56:37+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2016-04-04:/schumachers-buddhist-economics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been talking to a colleague recently about developing a project
on religion and economics under the auspices of the Religion and
Political Culture Network (RPCN) at the University of Manchester. This
has got me thinking about Buddhism, economics and Buddhist economics,
and has led me to reread Ernst …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been talking to a colleague recently about developing a project
on religion and economics under the auspices of the Religion and
Political Culture Network (RPCN) at the University of Manchester. This
has got me thinking about Buddhism, economics and Buddhist economics,
and has led me to reread Ernst Friedrich Schumacher’s classic essay
&lt;em&gt;Buddhist economics&lt;/em&gt;, first published in 1966, and available
online here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="uri" href="http://www.centerforneweconomics.org/buddhist-economics"&gt;http://www.centerforneweconomics.org/buddhist-economics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a fascinating piece, and though Schumacher’s arguments have
become commonplace among critics of mainstream economics, it’s
interesting just how current most of what he has to say sounds. Much of
what he has to say about the irrationality of certain assuptions in
academic economics is still being said today, for example by students
who are demanding changes in the way the subject is taught in
universities, tackled in a recent BBC radio documentary: &lt;a class="uri" href="http://bbc.in/1pBBGW9"&gt;http://bbc.in/1pBBGW9&lt;/a&gt;, and
in another broadcast last year: &lt;a class="uri" href="http://bbc.in/1y94uHF"&gt;http://bbc.in/1y94uHF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one of his claims about economics is arguably anachronistic: the
claim that economics considers only price in the use of different
natural resources, not whether they are renewable or not. I think that,
at least at the level of the economics of nations, the idea of
sustainability has gained significant traction since he was writing,
though he probably wouldn’t approve of the idea that the impact of
production on the environment can be ‘priced in’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a summary of Schumacher’s main points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="economics-is-not-value-free"&gt;1. Economics is not value-free&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He begins by regretting that leaders of Buddhist countries such as
Burma simultaneously say they want to retain and develop their Buddhist
traditions and ways of life, but seek advice from what he calls ‘modern’
and ‘materialist’ economists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might make sense if Buddhism and economics goverened two
completely distinct spheres of life. However, he argues that Buddhism,
which teaches Right Livelihood as part of the Eightfold Noble Path, must
have its own ideas about economics. On the other hand, he claims,
economics is not value-neutral, but is based on unacknowledged
metaphysical presuppositions that might be–and in fact are–in conflict
with the aims and premises of Buddhist teachings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-meaning-of-labour"&gt;2. The meaning of labour&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schumacher discusses attitudes to work as an example of the (mostly
unspoken) assumptions that distinguish modern economics from Buddhist
economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the ‘modern’ economics, labour is an evil. For the worker, its
something that destroys leisure and for which compensation in the form
of wages is required. For the employer, it is a cost of production. The
more production (in the case of the employer) or income (in the case of
the worker) can be had for the less work the better. So one central aim
of modern economics is to reduce the quantitity of work required for a
given amount of production through mechanisation and the division of
labour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Buddhist economics, in contrast, work is not a necessary evil,
but something that leads to a number of good outcomes apart from the
product itself, including the opportunity for the development of
character, and the opportunity to cooperate with others and in the
process overcome ‘ego-centredness’. Labour-saving innovations are not
necessarily bad, but their value depends on the extent to which they
free people from the heavy work to focus on more creating tasks, or to
the contrary, make work meaningless and repetitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-middle-way-and-consumption"&gt;3. The Middle Way and
consumption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern economics, Schumacher writes, assumes that wellbeing can be
measured by consumption, and therefore that greater annual rates of
consumption correspond to increased wellbeing. A Buddhist economist,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘… would consider this approach excessively irrational: since
consumption is merely a means to human well-being, the aim should be to
obtain the maximum of well-being with the minimum of consumption.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This is reminiscent of Southwold’s (1983: 188) opposition between
Buddhist ‘sapientalism’, ‘a rational strategy for ameliorating
experience by altering the mind rather than the environing world’, and
instrumentalism.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach could easily be misunderstood. One might assume that
the opposite of materialism is anti-materialism, or the pursuit of
poverty. But Schumacher points out that Buddhism is not about the
rejection of wealth, but the rejection of excessive attachment to
wealth. The Buddha tried and rejected ascetic austerities and then
promoted instead the moderation of the Middle Way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="localism-simplicity-and-non-violence"&gt;4. Localism, simplicity
and non-violence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schumacher argues that treating consumption as a means not an end in
itself means living simply (in order to leave oneself time to do what is
really important) and in accordance with non-violence (presumably
because consuming in a way that leads to violence would undermine the
proper goal of all consumption: liberation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using less in the way of resources also minimises the causes of
violence as it reduces the competition for resources. Schumacher also
claims–perhaps the this is the most debatable claim in the essay–that
trading across large distances brings people into potentially hostile
contact so that Buddhist economics would advocate local self-sufficience
and minimal dependence on international trade:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‘dependence on imports from afar and the consequent need to produce
for export to unknown and distant peoples is highly uneconomic and
justifiable only in exceptional cases and on a small scale.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="non-renewable-resources"&gt;5. Non-renewable resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Schumacher argues that Buddhist economics and modern
economics take a different view on non-renewable resources. For modern
economics, all resources are reduced to a money price, and whatever
resource is the cheapest price for each unit of output is preferable.
For Buddhist economics, in contrast, using non-renewables is living
parasitically off capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said above, this final point of criticism does sound rather
anachronistic now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schumacher, E. F. 1966. “Buddhist Economics”. In &lt;em&gt;Asia: A
Handbook&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Guy Wint. London: Anthony Blond Ltd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southwold, M. 1983. &lt;em&gt;Buddhism in Life&lt;/em&gt;. Manchester: Manchester
University Press.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Buddhism"></category><category term="‘Buddhist economics’"></category><category term="Schumacher"></category><category term="Southwold"></category></entry><entry><title>Needham’s review of Paul Veyne’s ‘Did the Greeks believe in their myths?’</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-17T13:45:57+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-08-17:/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my thoughts in my &lt;a href="../2015-08-17-rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-belief/"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to Needham’s review of Veyne’s book. The review is short, and
much is taken up with flattering comments on Veyne’s style, but overall
the conclusion is negative—he characterises the argument as ‘erratic and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my thoughts in my &lt;a href="../2015-08-17-rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-belief/"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to Needham’s review of Veyne’s book. The review is short, and
much is taken up with flattering comments on Veyne’s style, but overall
the conclusion is negative—he characterises the argument as ‘erratic and
inconsistent’. On my reading, Needham makes three substantive points,
which I shall deal with one by one here in order of importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only criticism that really has bite is that Veyne is vague about
what the key terms in his analysis—belief and truth—mean to him. Partly
on the basis of Veyne’s previous work, Needham reads &lt;em&gt;Did the
Greeks…?&lt;/em&gt; as an exercise in epistemological relativism, and makes a
version of the usual objection to the paradoxes of relativism: if truth
is always to be defined in local terms, in relation to historically
specific programmes of truth, as Veyne would have it, then what exactly
does Veyne mean when he says, absolutely, and not qualified by any
context, that truth is plural?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, Veyne actually concentrates not on belief but on
truth, but only to place himself in a further difficulty. He concedes
that ‘truth’ too means so many things, yet he passes over the variety of
theories of truth and, in the end, commits himself consistently to none.
The nearest he gets to a steady acceptance is to say that truths and
interests, which are both limited and arbitrary, are ‘two different
terms for the same thing’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham is right to call Veyne out for not clarifying his terms, and
attributing this weakness to strong epistemological relativism is not an
unreasonable interpretation. However, I believe another reading is
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne details the variety of ‘regimes of belief’ in terms of
different truth conditions and specific practices, such as the use of
footnotes in academic writing, with which they are associated. These
things are the specific form that believing has, historically taken. But
it is still possible to speak of believing in the abstract, as the
category to which all these concrete modes of belief belong. What is it
that makes the ordinary ancient Greek’s vague and lethargic belief in
gods and heroes an instance of the same class of phenomenon as the
mediaeval lawyer’s insistence on footnotes, and the modern newspaper
reader’s suspicion of bias? They are all specifications of the practical
and social relationship between thinker and what the thinker accepts as
truth. To put it more pithily, belief is about a relationship to a body
of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit, it’s not clear from Veyne’s text that this is what
&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; means by belief and truth, but it’s a reading that makes
sense of his concrete claims, and saves his general conclusions from
Needham’s anti-relativist criticism. Needham is right that Veyne is
unclear on this score, and clarifying the meaning of the general
category of belief, and of the general category of truth on which it
depends will be an important task for any ethnographic approach to
belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He complains that Veyne, in seeking to understand belief, did not
take into account the attempts of philosophers such as Wittgenstein,
Hume, Kant, and so on to do the same thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These writers were engaged in what Veyne describes as an exercise of
‘the constitutive imagination’. Like the ancient and modern historians
whom Veyne describes, they were engaged in shaping programmes of truth,
legitimising some ‘regimes of belief’ and delegitimising others. They
were not in the business of describing the plural programmes of truth of
others, and they would only have had a place in the book alongside the
mediaeval jurists and modern journalists that Veyne—as case studies of
the kind of second-order belief theory and practice that Veyne is
interested in describing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, Veyne is writing at a higher level of generalisation
or abstraction than Kant et al., and for a different purpose. The
philosophers’ question would not have been ‘Did the Greeks believe in
their myths’, but the logically posterior question, ‘Were the Greeks
right to (dis)believe in their myths?’, which is only meaningful once it
is established whether or not (or to what extent, in what senses) they
did, in fact, believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, Needham chides Veyne for not taking account of ‘sceptical
anthropology’. He argues that ethnographers have succeeded in explaining
the kinds god-language that Veyne’s question raises, but without
resorting to the notion of belief. He concludes that these writers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;confirm that it is not ‘pointless’, as Veyne proposes, to try to
determine the true thought of other peoples, but that we shall not do so
if we attribute our thoughts to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No page references are given in the review, but thanks to Google, it
is possible to trace the passage in Veyne’s book to which Needham
refers. Needham suggests that Veyne says it’s pointless ‘…to determine
the true thought of other peoples thought’. The ‘pointless’ here is
taken out of context and is quite misleading. In fact, Veyne was not
saying it was hopeless to try to understand ‘other people’s’ thought,
but that when faced with contradictory forms of thought, one must
recognise the plurality rather than trying to explain it away. The full
passage reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggling to determine ‘the’ true thought of these people is
pointless, and it is equally unproductive to attempt to resolve these
contradictory thoughts by attributing one to popular religion and the
other to the beliefs of the privileged social classes. (Veyne
1988:89)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sceptical approach that Needham recommends begins by setting
aside the question of belief. It may have found other explanations for
religious language, and they may be illuminating, but this approach
cannot even recognise the plurality of modes of belief that Veyne draws
our attention to and makes it his business to describe and
understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, then, Needham’s critical review does not persuade me that
Veyne’s way of understanding belief is not a really critical piece in
understanding human thought, though Needham is right to say that Veyne
is vague about his key terms. They’re still arguing in my head and Veyne
is still winning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Needham, Rodney. ‘Reviewed Work: Did the Greeks Believe in Their
Myths? An Essay on the Constitutive Imagination. by Paul Veyne, transl.
Paula Wissing’. Man (New Series), Vol. 25, No. 1 (Mar., 1990),
pp. 157-158.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Veyne, Paul. &lt;em&gt;Did the Greeks believe in their myths?: An essay on
the constitutive imagination&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
1988.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="belief scepticism"></category><category term="ethnography of belief"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="Rodney Needham"></category></entry><entry><title>Rodney Needham and Paul Veyne on religious belief</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-religious-belief.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-17T13:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-08-17:/rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-religious-belief.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804131"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by Rodney Needham
of Paul Veyne’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the Greeks
believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I was quite intrigued by this as these
two authors are representatives of two approaches to the study of
religious belief and the anthropology of belief I have been thinking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804131"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by Rodney Needham
of Paul Veyne’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the Greeks
believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I was quite intrigued by this as these
two authors are representatives of two approaches to the study of
religious belief and the anthropology of belief I have been thinking
about &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory/"&gt;for
a while&lt;/a&gt; . They have often squabbled in my head, and in my
imagination, Veyne always wins the argument, so I was curious to see
what Needham would make of Veyne’s argument and the strong implicit
critique of his own position it entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social scientists have a difficult relationship with religious
belief. On the one hand, belief is often absolutely central to accounts
of religious communities and practice: Group A carries out this practice
because of a belief X, religious innovator B used to do Y, so we can
conclude he believed Z, and so on. Such accounts are ubiquitous, in the
everyday language of religious people and non-specialists, &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;psychologists of
religion&lt;/a&gt;, and almost just as much, for all their denials, in the
language of social scientists. Because this model of religious life sees
belief-language as being a more or less reliable reflection of religious
people’s understanding of the world, it is known (mainly by its critics)
as ‘intellectualism’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, academic students of religion have long argued
that belief is just not what most religious traditions are about, and
that the use of the concept of belief is deeply misleading. I call this
position ‘belief scepticism’. Academic belief scepticism goes back at
least as far as William Robertson Smith’s 1889 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=oAfiFpR7sv8C"&gt;Lectures on the
Religion of the Semites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. There are many variations, but a
general outline of this position is as follows: we modern students of
religion think that religion is all about a set of propositions that
followers believe to be true, but this view of belief as propositional
and central to religious life is a relatively modern Christian
innovation; other religious traditions are more about practice or
symbolic expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This belief scepticism argument has also been extended to
Christianity, for example, by Abby Day, who recently &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review/"&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt;
that religion in the UK, including the that of her Christian
interviewees (not all were Christian), was about social belonging and
morality and not about propositional belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both intellectualism and belief scepticism have important
things to teach us about religious and other belief, I do not accept
either (1) that religious belief language is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; a
straightforward representation of systematically related propositions to
which followers assent, as the intellectualists are alleged to claim, or
(2) that belief-language &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; has another function (part of
practice, deference to a social system, expression of moral values) and
&lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; refers to propositional beliefs, except perhaps in the
case of (some) Christians, as the belief sceptics often argue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have long been a proponent of a &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory/"&gt;third
position&lt;/a&gt;, which I call the ‘ethnographic’ approach to belief—it
might equally be described as ‘historical’. This simply means
recognising that it is not only first order information—’God is three
persons in one substance’, ‘twins are birds’, ‘actions have
consequences’—that varies between persons, cultures, periods of history,
but also the second-order, meta-cognitive information and practices
relating to how one is supposed to relate cognitively and otherwise to
this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anthropologist and philosopher Rodney Needham wrote a long and
influential book making the belief-sceptic case, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=khWLQgAACAAJ"&gt;Belief, language
and experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1972). I have always found his arguments in the
book problematic and I’m always surprised by the deference with which
his argument is treated by contemporary anthropologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Veyne is a French historian of classical antiquity, who was
closely associated with Foucault. His 1983 book &lt;em&gt;Les Grecs ont-ils
cru à leurs mythes?&lt;/em&gt;, published in English translation in 1988 as
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the
Greeks believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is, I think, an exemplary
instance of an ethnographic approach to belief that takes into account
different styles, or ‘modes’ of belief, as much as the content to which
belief was applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His answer to the eponymous question is ‘yes and no’—the ordinary
Greek did not believe in myth in the same way that he believed in things
he had experienced directly, but he still believed that the events
recounted in myths were true. The different modes of truth were
distinguished by different truth conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne neatly demonstrates the importance of understanding the
plurality of modes of belief or ‘programmes of truth’ by contrasting the
attitudes of the Greek in the street with those of classical historians
such as Pausanias and Thucydides. The historians no less than hoi polloi
believe the events described by myths were true, but their activity was
motivated by a second-order imperative that insisted that there could
only be one programme of truth. The aim of their practice was to apply
reason, &lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt;, in order to reconcile the apparent
contradictions between &lt;em&gt;mythos—&lt;/em&gt;myths about gods and heroes—and
stories of the contemporary lives of ordinary people&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day, Abby. &lt;em&gt;Believing in belonging: Belief and social identity in
the modern world&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham, Rodney. &lt;em&gt;Belief, language, and experience&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford:
Blackwell, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="rw mbs"&gt;
Needham, Rodney. ‘Reviewed Work: &lt;cite&gt;Did the Greeks Believe in Their
Myths? An Essay on the Constitutive Imagination.&lt;/cite&gt; by Paul Veyne,
transl. Paula Wissing’. &lt;cite&gt;Man &lt;/cite&gt;(New Series), Vol. 25, No. 1
(Mar., 1990), pp. 157-158.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, William Robertson. &lt;em&gt;Lectures on the Religion of the
Semites: First series. The fundamental institutions&lt;/em&gt;. Appleton,
1889.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne, Paul. &lt;em&gt;Did the Greeks believe in their myths?: An essay on
the constitutive imagination&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
1988.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology of belief"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="belief scepticism"></category><category term="ethnography of belief"></category><category term="Greek myth"></category><category term="intellectualism"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="programmes of truth"></category><category term="regimes of belief"></category><category term="Rodney Needham"></category><category term="truth"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>The Meaning and End of Religion</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/the-meaning-and-end-of-religion.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-22T09:48:40+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-07-22:/the-meaning-and-end-of-religion.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend I read &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilfred_Cantwell_Smith"&gt;Wilfred
Cantwell Smith&lt;/a&gt;‘s &lt;em&gt;The Meaning and End of Religion&lt;/em&gt;
(1962)&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I knew a little about this book from Talal Asad’s 2001
&lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/3176697?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;
(jStor paywall), which I suppose is the main way most anthropologists of
religion have come to know its content too. Asad …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend I read &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wilfred_Cantwell_Smith"&gt;Wilfred
Cantwell Smith&lt;/a&gt;‘s &lt;em&gt;The Meaning and End of Religion&lt;/em&gt;
(1962)&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; I knew a little about this book from Talal Asad’s 2001
&lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/3176697?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;
(jStor paywall), which I suppose is the main way most anthropologists of
religion have come to know its content too. Asad lavishes praise on
Smith at the beginning of the article—the book is a ‘modern classic’,
and so on—but most of his article is a pretty unrelenting takedown. I
have always taken it for granted that Asad’s precis is a reliable
description of Smith’s position, but now I’ve actually read the book,
I’ve found that the argument is much more subtle, and that many (but not
all) of Asad’s criticisms are unfair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith begins his book by asking a question that had exercised many
other scholars before him: ‘What is religion?’. However, his answer is
quite original. Religion, he argues, is not a constant feature of human
experience, but a historical phenomenon which, being historical, had a
beginning and has continued to change. As it is changing and
heterogeneous, it sometimes has included things that at other times were
excluded. Therefore attempting to understand ‘religion’ as if it was a
stable thing is bound to be misleading. There is little we can say about
it as a category, except to trace its history, and he therefore calls
for the term to be dropped as an analytical tool altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asad writes that Smith is the first anti-essentialist theorist of
religion, but that’s not all he is, and for me he stands awkwardly
between the essentialists and the anti-essentialists. His account of the
history of the religion concept is in some ways much more wide-ranging
and complex than more recent accounts with which I’m more familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet in his claim that the experience of the transcendent is universal
and in some sense ahistorical, he looks like earlier generations of
anthropologists/sociologists/historians of religion, such as Durkheim
and Frazer, who sought to define religion as a trans-historical
category. And there are precedents, too, for the confessional position
that the true purpose of religious practice is a personal relationship
or encounter with the transcendent, for example, in the work of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evelyn_Underhill"&gt;Evelyn
Underhill&lt;/a&gt;.*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith predicted that sociologists would be uncomfortable with the
idea of building the category of the transcendent into their studies. It
does make me uncomfortable, and my instinct is to seek to historicize
the transcendent—is the transcendent/immanent opposition really
universal, as he assumes? can’t its development be traced? isn’t it
dependent on a certain kind of cosmology?—but the sophistication of
Smith’s writing has certainly made me a bit more open to the
idea….still, if you’ll permit me to mangle a metaphor, I can’t help
feeling that in throwing the bathwater out of the analytical bath, he’s
kept back a bit, mistaking it for a baby. If you see what I mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith argues that religion is a confusing term that is used to refer
to a number of different things. These things are, he says, quite
distinct, but they are conflated as a result of the contemporary
application of the term ‘religion’ to all of them. They are (48f):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(1) A personal relationship to transcendence, piety&lt;/strong&gt;
(in this sense we say someone is more or less religious than ten years
ago)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A system of beliefs, practices, values, or whatever,
extending over time and space&lt;/strong&gt; (in this sense we distinguish one
religion from another)—this can be further analysed into two separate
phenomena: &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt; the &lt;strong&gt;ideal religion&lt;/strong&gt; of
theologians, seldom if ever realised in life, and &lt;strong&gt;(3)&lt;/strong&gt;
the &lt;strong&gt;messy, human reality&lt;/strong&gt; of sociologists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(4) Religion in general&lt;/strong&gt;, as opposed to other realms
of life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Smith, the most important of all of these is the first, which he
proposes to call ‘faith’. He says that faith—a relationship of
obedience, submission or recognition of the transcendent, is a human
universal. This faith finds expression in practices, art, music,
theology and so on, but they are not it. The phenomena described by (2),
(3), and (4) are, unlike personal faith or piety, historical
developments and are therefore messy, heterogeneous, and without a
stable essence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conflation of these four aspects under the rubric of ‘religion’
leads to a number of problems. These problems are not consistently
distinguished by Smith, and the following enumeration may just be my
reading, but I think a passage near the very end of the book, where he
explains that his argument has relevance to religious people, to
students of religion, and for humanity at large, does indicate that he
thinks of them as separate problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 1:&lt;/strong&gt; the religious problem. As a religious
person, Smith thinks that faith, piety, the personal encounter of an
individual with the transcendent, is undermined when people conflate it
with its expression. The result is a focus on contingent externals,
rather than the relationship itself. He doesn’t argue, I think, that the
external expressions of faith is unimportant (this is key to my
disagreement with Asad) but rather that treating them as
&lt;em&gt;religion&lt;/em&gt; may lead people to neglect faith and to become too
attached to specifics that should be seen as accidents of
history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 2:&lt;/strong&gt; the sociological problem. As the
meaning of the term ‘religion’ has a history, it is confusing when
applied anachronistically across periods in history, or ethnocentrically
to other cultures, and it should be dropped. For instance, the idea that
religion is distinguished from the secular is distinctively a
characteristic of European religion, because there Christianity came to
dominate, but existed alongside political traditions with classical
roots, which only then were understood as secular. When looking at
specific traditions, such as Buddhism or Islam, we should not look for a
defining essence or genius, but accept that they are ever branching,
heterogeneous, contingent accumulations. When trying to understand the
influence of a religious tradition on an individual follower of that
tradition, we can take into account only those aspects of the tradition
of which the follower is aware, rather than trying to define the essence
of the religion explaining his or her actions in the light of that
essence.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Problem 3:&lt;/strong&gt; the human problem. Smith suggests
that the reification of religion is the cause of conflict. If we
recognised the universality of the human relationship with
transcendence—that is, of faith—we’d learn to tolerate and appreciate
each other’s concrete expressions of that relationship.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* Thanks to my colleague, Benjamin Wood for pointing me to
Underhill’s work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asad, Talal. “Reading a Modern Classic: WC Smith’s” The Meaning and
End of Religion”.” &lt;em&gt;History of Religions&lt;/em&gt; (2001): 205-222.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, Wilfred Cantwell. &lt;em&gt;The meaning and end of religion&lt;/em&gt;.
Fortress Press, 1963.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underhill, Evelyn. &lt;em&gt;Mysticism: A study in the nature and
development of man’s spiritual consciousness&lt;/em&gt;. Jack Books, 1930.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>‘Neoliberalism’ as ‘conceptual trash heap’</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/neoliberalism-as-conceptual-trash-heap.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-06T09:31:19+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-07-06:/neoliberalism-as-conceptual-trash-heap.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post in a long time. Over the last year I moved to
Manchester and started teaching full time. I hope to return to blogging
from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve seen the transcript of the 2012 &lt;a href="../201-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;GDAT debate on the
concept of neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt;, which is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post in a long time. Over the last year I moved to
Manchester and started teaching full time. I hope to return to blogging
from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve seen the transcript of the 2012 &lt;a href="../201-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;GDAT debate on the
concept of neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt;, which is due to be published in JRAI next
year. I spoke in the debate as second proposer for the (resoundingly
defeated!) motion &lt;em&gt;The concept of neoliberalism has become an
obstacle to the anthropological understanding of the twenty-first
century&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of an article I came across a few months ago: &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12116-009-9040-5"&gt;Boas,
Taylor C., and Jordan Gans-Morse. “Neoliberalism: From new liberal
philosophy to anti-liberal slogan.” &lt;em&gt;Studies in Comparative
International Development&lt;/em&gt; 44.2 (2009): 137-161.&lt;/a&gt; The argument is
similar to the one James Laidlaw and I made in the debate but it is
based on a much more systematic review of social scientific literature
than we were able to present in our short speeches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="page" title="Page 2"&gt;
&lt;div class="section"&gt;
&lt;div class="layoutArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="column"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a review of 148 articles on neoliberalism published in the top
comparative politics, development, and Latin American studies journals
between 1990 and 2004, we did not find a single article focused on the
definition and usage of neoliberalism, nor are we aware of one published
elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the use of neoliberalism in the contemporary study of political
economy differs from that of other normatively charged social science
concepts in three potentially problematic ways. First, its negative
normative valence and connotations of radicalism have produced
asymmetric patterns of use across ideological divides. Second, scholars
who do use the term neoliberalism tend not to define it in empirical
research, even when it is an important independent or dependent
variable. And third, the term is applied to multiple distinct phenomena,
from a set of economic policies or development model to an ideology or
academic paradigm. In present usage, neoliberalism conveys little common
substantive meaning but serves as a clear indicator that one does not
evaluate free markets positively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors make a very interesting argument that the origin of the
term’s contemporary academic usage lies in South American critiques of
Pinochet in the 1970s and 80s. Pinochet was applying radical economic
policies formulated by the ‘Chicago Boys’, based on the thought of Hayek
and Friedman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once established as a common term among Spanish-speaking scholars,
neoliberalism diffused directly into the English-language study of
political economy, such that its present-day usage is heir to the
critical Latin American scholarship of the 1970s and 1980s. In one very
important way, contemporary usage of neoliberalism has changed
fundamentally since that period: it no longer denotes a new form of
liberalism with specific features and empirical referents, but has
become a vague term that can mean virtually anything as long as it
refers to normatively negative phenomena associated with free markets.
As the term neoliberalism has diffused broadly, nothing has prevented
its meaning from drifting even more broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This goes some way to explaining the fact that some of the strongest
defenders of the concept of neoliberalism in the discussion part of the
debate were scholars working on Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also suggest an ingenious explanation of the mechanism by which
the vagueness of ‘neoliberalism’ is established and maintained. They
distinguish contested concepts from contested terms. In the case of
neoliberalism, the concepts are ideas associated with free markets. The
term is the normatively loaded ‘neoliberalism’, which is applied only by
those who are critical of the concepts. Where a term is agreed upon, and
only the underlying concepts are contested, there’s a shared incentive
to police the boundaries of the term. But…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the case of neoliberalism, the conjunction of terminological
contestation and the contested normative valence of the underlying
concepts to which it can refer short circuits debate over the term’s
meaning and proper application. Because the normative valence of free
market phenomena is contested, some scholars have an incentive to
suggest that the negative aspects of markets are more widespread,
whereas others have an incentive to argue that their positive aspects
are more prevalent. Those who use neoliberalism, however, participate in
only one side of this debate. To contest the intension and extension of
neoliberalism, by arguing that certain cases do not qualify or that
certain definitional criteria do not belong, would be to suggest that
the negative aspects of markets are not as widespread as others
maintain—undercutting the still-unresolved argument about whether the
free market is ultimately good or bad. The result is that neoliberalism
has become a conceptual trash heap capable of accommodating multiple
distasteful phenomena without much argument as to whether one or the
other component really belongs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="debate"></category><category term="gdat"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Announcing: Ignorance Studies Listserv</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/announcing-ignorance-studies-listserv.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-26T14:54:46+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2014-01-26:/announcing-ignorance-studies-listserv.html</id><content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="Anthropology of Ignorance" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/ignorance.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;Anthropology of Ignorance&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve set up a JISCMail mailing list for discussion of the social
scientific study of ignorance. The list will be publicly archived. To
subscribe or contribute, click &lt;a href="https://www.jiscmail.ac.uk/cgi-bin/webadmin?A0=IGNORANCE-STUDIES"&gt;HERE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get in touch with me if you have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="ignorance"></category><category term="sociology"></category></entry><entry><title>Speaking Ethically Across Borders Conference: Registration Open!</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/speaking-ethically-across-borders-conference-registration-open.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-12-11T21:54:28+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-12-11:/speaking-ethically-across-borders-conference-registration-open.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Registration is now open for the conference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="speaking-ethically-across-borders-interdisciplinary-approaches"&gt;Speaking
Ethically Across Borders: Interdisciplinary Approaches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8-10 January 2014&lt;br/&gt;
CRASSH, University of Cambridge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With lectures by: Michael Lambek (Toronto) and Simon Coleman
(Toronto).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including papers by: Michael Lempert (Michigan), John Marenbon
(Cambridge), Carlo Severi (EHESS), Hallvard Lillehammer (Birbeck).&lt;br/&gt;
***For registration and further details …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Registration is now open for the conference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="speaking-ethically-across-borders-interdisciplinary-approaches"&gt;Speaking
Ethically Across Borders: Interdisciplinary Approaches&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8-10 January 2014&lt;br/&gt;
CRASSH, University of Cambridge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With lectures by: Michael Lambek (Toronto) and Simon Coleman
(Toronto).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Including papers by: Michael Lempert (Michigan), John Marenbon
(Cambridge), Carlo Severi (EHESS), Hallvard Lillehammer (Birbeck).&lt;br/&gt;
***For registration and further details: &lt;a class="uri" href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/events/25021"&gt;http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/events/25021&lt;/a&gt; ***&lt;br/&gt;
***The Facebook page can be viewed here: &lt;a class="uri" href="https://www.facebook.com/events/341661642641952/"&gt;https://www.facebook.com/events/341661642641952/&lt;/a&gt;
***&lt;br/&gt;
Convenors: Jonathan Mair (jonathan.mair@manchester.ac.uk) and Nicholas
Evans (ne228@cam.ac.uk)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent years have seen a dramatic growth in the study of ethics among
social anthropologists. Much of this growth has been due to the
assimilation into anthropological thinking of virtue ethics building on
two streams of theoretical work: that of Foucault, and that of virtue
ethicists working in the Anglo-Saxon philosophical tradition. Proponents
of the virtue-ethics approach in anthropology argue that a focus on
self-cultivation as a process allows for sufficient attention to be paid
to self-conscious reflection. Reflection and the freedom it entails,
they argue, are essential aspects of ethical life that traditional
social scientific approaches to ethics – Durkheimian approaches – simply
ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There appears to remain an area of ethical experience, however, that
neither approach can easily accommodate. Since virtue ethics sees
ethical judgment as the result of cultivation within a self-conscious
ethical tradition, it can no more account for ethical judgment outside
of or between traditions than the Durkheimian approach can. Yet history
is full of situations in which multiple, self-conscious ethical
traditions meet, and in which people try to judge each other, persuade
each other, or draw lessons from each other across the borders that
separate those traditions. These situations are what we call ‘speaking
ethically across borders’, and this is the phenomenon that the
conference will aim to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these situations, are people limited to using values with which
they are already familiar to interpret and judge other values? Or can
they genuinely learn from alternative ethical systems? If so, on what
conditions does this process depend? Is the capacity for or disposition
towards a cosmopolitan attitude to ethics itself a culturally specific
norm or a virtue to be perfected, or is it a necessary aspect of ethical
thought? Ethnographically speaking, how have people in fact used the
intellectual resources provided by one ethical tradition to judge
others? How have they sought to borrow from other traditions, or to
persuade followers of other traditions to adopt novel values and
practices? What meta-ethics have specific traditions proposed to govern
the relationship of members of the tradition to the mores of other
traditions?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sponsored by: Centre for Research in the Arts, Social Sciences and
Humanities (CRASSH); The Division of Social Anthropology, University of
Cambridge; St. John’s College, Cambridge; King’s College, Cambridge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="cambridge"></category><category term="coleman"></category><category term="conference"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="lambek"></category><category term="philosophy"></category><category term="anthropology of ethics"></category><category term="ethics across borders"></category></entry><entry><title>Abby Day’s Believing in Belonging: Review</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-30T15:16:07+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-06-30:/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s my review of Abby Day’s Believing in Belonging which appeared
in last year’s edition of the &lt;a href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/arrs/2012/00000003/00000001/art00019"&gt;Journal
of Religion and Society&lt;/a&gt;. Though I didn’t quite buy the theoretical
argument of the book, I thought the substantive work on people’s
attitudes towards institutionalised religion, gods …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s my review of Abby Day’s Believing in Belonging which appeared
in last year’s edition of the &lt;a href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/arrs/2012/00000003/00000001/art00019"&gt;Journal
of Religion and Society&lt;/a&gt;. Though I didn’t quite buy the theoretical
argument of the book, I thought the substantive work on people’s
attitudes towards institutionalised religion, gods, ghosts and fate was
fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commentary on the census is also very useful. I referred to that
aspect of the work in a &lt;a href="../2012-11-16-evolution-and-religion"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, where I
questioned an evolutionary explanation of religion that relied on data
from historical censuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="review-of-believing-in-belonging-by-abby-day"&gt;Review of
&lt;em&gt;Believing in Belonging&lt;/em&gt; by Abby Day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/arrs;jsessionid=1gxhglhhneg0a.victoria" title="Religion and Society: Advances in Research"&gt;Religion and Society:
Advances in Research&lt;/a&gt;, Volume 3, Number 1, 2012 , pp. 211-241(31)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Believing in Belonging&lt;/em&gt; is a study based mainly on a series
of interviews conducted in the early 2000s in the north of England.
Suspecting that sociological studies of religious affiliation were
failing to capture something important, Day asked her interviewees
instead about ‘belief’. In the substantive chapters she outlines the
main issues that emerged from these conversations: community and
identity, relations with kin, enduring relations with the dead, the
operation of fate or providence, and the importance of morality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting finding relates to a puzzle about contemporary
religious belief. In the 2001 census, which was the first to include a
question on religious identity, 72% of respondents identified themselves
as Christian. This was interpreted jubilantly by many, Day notes, as a
refutation of the secularization thesis. The census was not the first
survey to show that a high proportion of British people continue to
identify themselves as Christian, but it added to a longstanding
sociological puzzle: while a high proportion of people in postwar Europe
are still willing to call themselves Christian, other markers of
religion, such as participation in acts of worship, show a dramatic and
continuing decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two established explanations for this discrepancy. One is
that many of the self-identified Christians are ‘nominal’ Christians,
who identify themselves as Christian if asked, and may attend church for
weddings and funerals, but otherwise do not think twice about belief. On
this interpretation, the high rates of religious identification in
surveys such as the census tell us little or nothing about the decline
of belief in religion. The other explanation, most influentially
advanced by Grace Davie, is that the phenomenon is just another aspect
of the individualization of western societies, in which traditional
communal institutions have lost their authority and people engage with
culture on their own terms. On this view, the fall in church attendance
cannot be taken as evidence of a corresponding loss of belief, rather,
people continue ‘believing without belonging’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day’s research supports neither explanation. She finds that her
interviewees can be divided into ‘theocentrics’, who see a relationship
with God at the center of everything they do, and ‘anthropocentrics’,
who do not. Theocentrics tend to be quite hostile in their evaluation of
anthropocentrics, and vice versa. But the surprising and significant
finding is that the boundaries of these groups do not coincide with the
boundary between those who identify themselves as belonging to a
religion and those who do not. About half of the interviewees who
identified themselves as Christian were ‘anthropocentric’, and many of
those were assertively atheist as well as rejecting the authority of
institutional religion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a problem for the ‘believing without belonging’ school,
because it suggests that little can be assumed about people’s acceptance
of religious beliefs on the basis of their self-declared religious
identity. On the other hand, many ‘anthropocentric’ respondents, whether
or not they felt they belonged to a particular religion, did believe
they had experienced ghosts, and that the hand of fate acted in their
lives. This means that neither falling church attendances or even
outright antipathy to religion can be taken as clear evidence of
rationalization of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day’s own interpretation of her findings is that claiming, or
‘performing’, religious identity through surveys and narratives is a way
of asserting a sort of ascribed cultural heritage, and simultaneously
excluding ethnic others from it. Beliefs about other things—values, the
dead, and so on—are used in the same way to express the importance of
various social relationships, and often to exclude weak groups including
women and children. Day’s ‘neo-Durkheimian’ conclusion is that belief is
ultimately a matter of ‘the social’: ‘believing in belonging’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the detail of Day’s interviews is of interest. For example,
the way in which informants sometimes reveal their own awareness of
having decided to believe that they can speak to their kin beyond the
grave, because the alternative would be unbearable, or the fact that
ghosts are experienced in an embodied, sensually rich way, but rarely
visually, or that among her respondents, only deceased kin were
experienced in this way, not friends or unrelated strangers.
Interviewees say they believe morality is doing to others as one would
be done by, but in practice, they mean ‘doing to’ people like
themselves, and various ethnic, or gendered ‘others’ turn out not to
merit the same treatment. Many ‘anthropocentric’ people say that being
culturally Christian means that their values are based on the Ten
Commandments, and do not notice that they have tacitly edited out
Commandments I – IV, which stipulate proper behavior in relation to
God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This material alone makes the book a valuable contribution to the
literature. However, in terms of its theoretical aims—to provide a sound
basis for understanding belief—the book is less successful. Day is
ambitious in this respect and there are theoretical claims throughout.
Here space allows me to mention only the most important of them, Day’s
argument (drawing on Austin and Butler) that belief should be understood
as ‘performative’ in the sense that the narration of beliefs brings
about concrete effects. However, the claim is nowhere clearly explained,
and Day’s usage is slippery: sometimes the effect of performance is the
creation of a community of identity or some other object of belief,
sometimes it is the creation of the belief itself, sometimes she seems
to be claiming that the performance &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; is the belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason that defining ‘belief’ is so important to Day’s
argument—and this is also the reason it is so difficult to define—is
that she seeks to displace the concept of ‘religion’ from its central
position in social scientific work, but seems to want to replace it with
an equivalent concept that covers much the same ground, including fate,
morality and communication with the dead. But there is no reason to
think that the different things the interviewees speak about under the
rubric of ‘belief’ cover, from their point of view, a single field of
thought or activity, and therefore no reason to expect to be able to
find a unifying definition, or even that a family resemblance
relationship obtains between them. Day sets out to replace the survey
designers’ blunt questions about religious affiliation, which assume too
much, with a more inductive approach, but the design of her structured
interviews, starting with the question, ‘What do you believe in?’
incorporates its own assumptions, above all that there is a single,
coherent phenomenon that corresponds to ‘believing in’. Day’s
descriptions of the anxiety evoked in her participants by her first
question—for instance, ‘Sometimes informants demonstrated surprise at
the question and needed a few seconds to gather his or her [sic]
thoughts. Some physically drew back and looked at me in shock…’
(p. 41)—suggest that for them ‘believing in’ corresponded to no clearly
defined or salient category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day has not solved the problem of belief, but notwithstanding these
limitations, her book is an important contribution to the literature
that has significant implications for future empirical and theoretical
work, as well as for public policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Abby Day"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="census"></category><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="fate"></category><category term="ghosts"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="uk"></category></entry><entry><title>Cultures of Belief — post-print version of article</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-post-print-version-of-article.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-10T16:42:23+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-04-10:/cultures-of-belief-post-print-version-of-article.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As promised, here’s a post-print version of my Cultures of Belief
article, which was published in Anthropological Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/pdf/cultures-of-belief-post-print.pdf" title="Cultures of Belief - post-print pdf"&gt;cultures-of-belief-post-print&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text is identical to the journal version, but the formatting is
different — this is the version I’m allowed to distribute according to
the publishing agreement. If you have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As promised, here’s a post-print version of my Cultures of Belief
article, which was published in Anthropological Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/pdf/cultures-of-belief-post-print.pdf" title="Cultures of Belief - post-print pdf"&gt;cultures-of-belief-post-print&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text is identical to the journal version, but the formatting is
different — this is the version I’m allowed to distribute according to
the publishing agreement. If you have access to the journal, for example
through a library, you can see a prettier version &lt;a href="http://ant.sagepub.com/content/12/4/448"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="Evangelicals"></category><category term="gods"></category><category term="Greece"></category><category term="Judaism"></category><category term="Maimonides"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Cultures of Belief – New paper out in Anthropological Theory</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-10T15:31:14+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-04-10:/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just had a new paper out in &lt;a href="http://ant.sagepub.com/content/12/4/448.full.pdf+html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anthropological
Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — this is behind a paywall, I’ll make a post-print
version available through this website soon for those who don’t have
access to the journal through an academic library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is titled ‘Cultures of ignorance’. In a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just had a new paper out in &lt;a href="http://ant.sagepub.com/content/12/4/448.full.pdf+html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anthropological
Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — this is behind a paywall, I’ll make a post-print
version available through this website soon for those who don’t have
access to the journal through an academic library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is titled ‘Cultures of ignorance’. In a nutshell, the
argument is that academic students of religion have settled on a way of
accounting for religious language and thought that distinguishes
ordinary, everyday belief from religious belief. The former is
understood to be literal and practical. The latter, by contrast, is
taken to be indirect, metaphorical, symbolic, affective, moral and so
on, and by implication &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be about propositional belief.
Drawing on my own field research in northern China’s Inner Mongolia, I
argue that there are ways of relating to a body of true knowledge that
fit neither of these models. I argue that in order to understand what is
going on in this situation and many others we need to develop an
ethnographic sensibility to locally specific ‘cultures of belief’. To
get this project off to a start, I suggest some initial building blocks
for a general anthropology of belief, based on religious thought in
ancient Greece, mediaeval Judaism, and contemporary US Evangelism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In popular thought about the meaning of religion, as well as
established debates in anthropology, religious belief is interpreted as
either a commitment to a clear set of propositions, or as a non-literal,
symbolic, ethical or social commitment. Anthropologists have tended to
support the latter of these positions, so much so that this can now be
seen as the ‘anthropological’ position; it is also characteristic of the
view of scholars in related disciplines, such as religious studies. This
article argues for a third possibility: that religious (and other)
believers are often engaged in complex, reflexive practices that
stipulate specific cognitive and non-cognitive relationships to
propositional content. This is demonstrated with reference to
contemporary Buddhism in Inner Mongolia, China. The author argues that
the existence of such cultures of belief demonstrates there is a need
for a systematic anthropological theory of belief and suggests some
sources that may contribute to its formulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mair, J., 2013. Cultures of belief. &lt;em&gt;Anthropological Theory&lt;/em&gt;,
12(4), pp.448–466.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="Buddhism"></category><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="Judaism"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Literacy, religious renaissance and the 'morality system'</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/literacy-religious-renaissance-and-the-morality-system.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-04T20:00:23+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-04-04:/literacy-religious-renaissance-and-the-morality-system.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-post from ethics.CRASSH.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="felicitas-becker-on-islamic-reformism-and-sufi-traditionalism-in-tanzania"&gt;Felicitas
Becker on Islamic reformism and Sufi traditionalism in Tanzania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve just read two fascinating papers by &lt;a href="http://www.hist.cam.ac.uk/directory/fmb26@cam.ac.uk"&gt;Felicitas
Becker&lt;/a&gt; on moral conflict in East Africa. Both papers describe the
relationship between Islamist reformers and Sufi-influenced
traditionalists in rural Tanzania. Broadly speaking, the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-post from ethics.CRASSH.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="felicitas-becker-on-islamic-reformism-and-sufi-traditionalism-in-tanzania"&gt;Felicitas
Becker on Islamic reformism and Sufi traditionalism in Tanzania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve just read two fascinating papers by &lt;a href="http://www.hist.cam.ac.uk/directory/fmb26@cam.ac.uk"&gt;Felicitas
Becker&lt;/a&gt; on moral conflict in East Africa. Both papers describe the
relationship between Islamist reformers and Sufi-influenced
traditionalists in rural Tanzania. Broadly speaking, the Islamists are
young, have international connections (though these are limited), and
their leaders claim legitimacy as a result of their scriptural
scholarship. The traditionalists are drawn from the older generations
and derive their authority from their descent from founders of local
mosques, or from their place in a chain of transmission of oral
knowledge. Most local people, Becker notes, consider themselves Muslims,
but observe the debates between the two groups without feeling the need
to declare themselves partisans of either side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the papers, ‘Islamic Reform and Historical Change in the Care
of the Dead’ (2009) focuses on disagreements between the two parties
around funerary practices, which take on great importance in this
context. Traditionalists have elaborate funerals in which prayers and
the Quran are recited over the funeral procession and the deceased is
read instructions on how to meet the angels after the burial is
complete. To the elders who represent this tradition, these measures
show that they are more punctilious in caring for the dead than their
nomadic forebears who, before the adoption of Islamic usages, would
abandon settlements along with the corpses of the dead. To the
reformists, the intercessions on behalf of, and interaction with, the
deceased are accretions that are not justified by Quran or Hadith and
must therefore be relinquished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other paper, ‘Rural Islamism during the “War on Terror”‘ (2006)
considers a wider range of disagreements over practice, and also
addresses the question of how far the reformers, who are nicknamed by
other ‘Al Qaeda’, are in fact part of a coherent ‘international terror’
movement. Becker’s admirably nuanced conclusion, if I understand it
correctly, is that although they are politically activist in theory, and
in a way that could potentially lead to violent conflict, the political
plank of their programme finds no traction with local concerns and is
therefore barely a live part of their practice, while the international
connections are tenuous. Meanwhile, the other aspect of their programme,
the claim that scriptural scholarship is the sole source of religious
legitimacy has found great support among the population, and even
grudging assent among those who find themselves on the opposite side of
debates about specific practices. This aspect of Becker’s material makes
it interesting in terms of the CRASSH Speaking Ethically Across Borders
Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-morality-system-and-literacy"&gt;The ‘morality system’ and
literacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2006 paper, Becker notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the opinions expounded by &lt;em&gt;Ansaar&lt;/em&gt; [the reformists/Islamists]
consistently tend towards the imposition of stricter rules. They are
more concerned than others about the loss of ritual purity through
contact with the opposite sex; they support a ban on alcohol and have
suggested that smoking, too, is &lt;em&gt;haram&lt;/em&gt;, religiously prohibited.
… They have also introduced new forms of veiling to Rwangwa, have
changed standards for &lt;em&gt;halal&lt;/em&gt; (religiously correct) slaughter and
have questioned the acceptability of established ways of dealing with
witchcraft. (Becker 2006: 594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me think about the relation of literacy and forms of
ethics. Much recent anthropological work on ethics has taken on a
distinction from philosophy between virtue ethics and what Bernard
Williams calls the ‘morality system’. The morality system is about
judgment of acts against legalistic codes of behaviour, lists of
obligations and taboos, and it leads to a concern with the refinement of
rules for particular circumstances, and with moral dilemmas. Virtue
ethics is about the judgment of character against models of excellence,
and leads to a concern with the identification of exemplars, and with
pedagogical techniques that lead to the cultivation of particular
virtues (including what Foucault calls ‘techniques of the self’).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of anthropological work on Islamic reformists has emphasised
the way in which their reforms are connected to virtue ethical
programmes of character development, but I wonder if there’s a general
relationship between reformist movements that base legitimacy on
scriptural sources and the importance of the ‘morality system’.
Character-based ethics requires a good deal of interpretation in order
to work out how an exemplar would act in the current situation (see
Humphrey 1997 on this). Virtues that are partly or mainly about embodied
dispositions are apt to be expressed in imagistic forms that
underdetermine their expression (Carrithers 1990). Is it difficult to
combine this interpretative flexibility and the autonomy it implies with
an insistence on submission to scripture as a sole source of
authority?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Becker’s Tanzanian case study, the traditionalist elders apply
this kind of reasoning to the conduct of funerals. The reformists argue
from scripture that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Prophet, peace be upon him, prohibits the corpse [to be sung to],
that is to say, when we get up to go to the graveyard to bury someone,
we are required to be quiet and to ponder that our fellow Muslim has
died and we will die too. Therefore we must be quiet. And the Prophet
says don’t follow the hearse with any sort of noise, let people be quiet
and reflect. (Becker 2006: 592)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sufis’ riposte is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the days of the prophet, the graves were situated very close to
the houses of the liv- ing. But our graves are far from our villages.
Moreover, our faith is not as strong as that of the first Muslims. Were
we to go to the graveyard in silence, our thoughts might start to wander
and some might start to discuss, say, football on the way to the grave!
So our elders decided we had better recite the shahada on the way to the
grave, to keep our minds focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could, I think, be interpreted as a more character-based
approach to ethics. Though the traditionalists accept the idea that
scripture, and not established custom, is the proper arbiter of
practice, they maintain enough autonomy from it to interpret it in the
light of specific local and personal conditions. Perhaps this shows that
they are more concerned with emulating the underlying character
expressed by the Prophet’s actions, something that can never be entirely
captured in words, because it is always contextual, rather than
reproducing the actions, which can be more precisely described in the
text, themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to reach a conclusion on this question on the basis of
this material alone, but perhaps a comparative approach would turn up a
regular association between text-based revival movements
(i.e. renaissances — Goody 2009), and a shift away from a concern with
character and towards a concern with moral rules. Or the shift might be
away from a complex character approach, with multiple, perhaps mutually
incompatible, virtues or exemplars available to the moral subject,
towards a simpler character approach which focuses all effort on the
single virtue of perfect submission to the authority of the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main texts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becker, F., 2006. Rural Islamism during the “war on terror”: A
Tanzanian case study. &lt;em&gt;African Affairs&lt;/em&gt;, 105(421),
pp.583–603.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becker, F., 2011. Islamic Reform and Historical Change in the Care of
the Dead: Conflicts Over Funerary Practice Among Tanzanian Muslims.
&lt;em&gt;Africa&lt;/em&gt;, 79(03), pp.416–434.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further reading&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carrithers, M., 1990. Jainism and Buddhism as enduring historical
streams. &lt;em&gt;JASO (Journal of the Anthropological Society of
Oxford)&lt;/em&gt;, 21(2), pp.141–163.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faubion, J.D., 2001. Toward an Anthropology of Ethics: Foucault and
the Pedagogies of Autopoiesis. &lt;em&gt;Representations&lt;/em&gt;, (74),
pp.83–104. Available at:
http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/rep.2001.74.1.83.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foucault, M., 1990. &lt;em&gt;The history of sexuality volume 3: the care
of the self&lt;/em&gt;, London: Penguin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goody, J., 2009. &lt;em&gt;Renaissances&lt;/em&gt;, Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humphrey, C. 1997. Exemplars and rules: aspects of the discourse of
moralities in Mongolia. In Howell, S. (ed). &lt;em&gt;The ethnography of
moralities&lt;/em&gt;. London: Routledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laidlaw, J., 2002. For An Anthropology Of Ethics And Freedom.
&lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute&lt;/em&gt;, 8(2),
pp.311–332.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Williams, B.A.O., 1985. &lt;em&gt;Ethics and the limits of philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,
Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology of ethics"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="Felicitas Becker"></category><category term="funerary practice"></category><category term="Islam"></category><category term="Islamism"></category><category term="morality system"></category><category term="Sufism"></category><category term="Tanzania"></category><category term="virtue ethics"></category></entry><entry><title>New blog… ethics.CRASSH</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/new-blog-ethicscrassh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-03-28T17:26:06+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T13:22:46+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-03-28:/new-blog-ethicscrassh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve launched a new website as part of my current project at CRASSH.
It’s called &lt;a href="http://ethics.crassh.cam.ac.uk"&gt;ethics.CRASSH&lt;/a&gt;
and at the moment it’s covering the Speaking Ethically Across Borders
Project, which has been running as a reading group this year. Several of
the participants have already posted commentaries …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve launched a new website as part of my current project at CRASSH.
It’s called &lt;a href="http://ethics.crassh.cam.ac.uk"&gt;ethics.CRASSH&lt;/a&gt;
and at the moment it’s covering the Speaking Ethically Across Borders
Project, which has been running as a reading group this year. Several of
the participants have already posted commentaries on the texts we’ve
been reading. If things go well, I hope this will develop as a more
general resource for interdisciplinary studies of ethics in Cambridge
and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in writing something for the blog, please let
me know.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category></entry><entry><title>Stuart Hall on rootless cosmopolitanism</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/stuart-hall-on-rootless-cosmopolitanism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-31T15:51:46+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-01-31:/stuart-hall-on-rootless-cosmopolitanism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interesting interview with Stuart Hall, in which he speaks
about cosmopolitanism and rootedness — relevant to the previous
post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sms.cam.ac.uk/media/1119965"&gt;http://www.sms.cam.ac.uk/media/1119965&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pnina Werbner interviewing — I’ve transcribed the most relevant bit
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23.30&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PW: Can you be a cosmopolitan if you …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s an interesting interview with Stuart Hall, in which he speaks
about cosmopolitanism and rootedness — relevant to the previous
post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sms.cam.ac.uk/media/1119965"&gt;http://www.sms.cam.ac.uk/media/1119965&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pnina Werbner interviewing — I’ve transcribed the most relevant bit
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;23.30&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PW: Can you be a cosmopolitan if you don’t have to commitments to a
place or people or maybe even culture? Is it possible to be a
cosmopolitan without this rootedness somewhere?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SH: Well I would have said not, and I think I’m afraid of the word
because it sort of suggests that. It sort of invokes a kind of
cultureless, rootedless image of a person who’s free-floating sampling
all the cultures, like my global entrepreneur in the first-class waiting
room of some airport is a good idea – they love a bit of Japanese
cooking, Indian cooking here, French cuisine there. They sample all of
them but none comes from a attachment to a particular way of handling
food et cetera. That doesn’t mean you need to eat that way all the time
but you sort of know what it is like to be attached. I think that
without that the old Marxist jibe ‘rootless cosmopolitanism’ has some
substance to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think in many ways, this is where we encounter an interesting
interface with one aspect of liberalism which exactly thinks we can only
really calculate what individuals are like when we free them from all
their attachments: no religion, no culture nothing, free floating atoms
contracting with other free floating atoms, and I think this is exactly
one of the limitations of liberalism. It has never understood culture,
not [that] it has never sunk itself into culture, it has never
*understood* culture. This idea of the atomised individual has of course
played it’s role. The notion of the rule of law depends on a certain
abstraction from cultures and particularities, so it does have it’s
value, but it’s never understood that it’s always underpinned by its own
culture. There’s no liberal democracy that doesn’t have roots in a
particular community….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I believe in that locatedness, in position, attachment, but I
believe that those are rarely singular. I don’t think they overlap, that
the attachment to community is the same as the attachment to culture,
and I think that all of that has to be aware of its limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology of ethics"></category><category term="ethics across borders"></category><category term="cosmopolitanism"></category><category term="Pnina Werbner"></category><category term="Stuart Hall"></category></entry><entry><title>Rooted Cosmopolitanism</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/rooted-cosmopolitanism.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-01-31T15:44:43+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-01-31:/rooted-cosmopolitanism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 834px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Waterhouse-Diogenes.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/7a/Waterhouse-Diogenes.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
Diogenes the Cynic, a citizen of the world, in a painting by John
William Waterhouse
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday saw the first of a series of reading groups that I’m
organizing at &lt;a href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;CRASSH&lt;/a&gt; on the
subject of &lt;a href="../2012-12-07-crassh-project-speaking-ethically-across-borders" title="CRASSH Project: Speaking Ethically Across Borders"&gt;ethical
conversations across borders&lt;/a&gt;. There will be four sessions this term,
each dealing with a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 834px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Waterhouse-Diogenes.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/7a/Waterhouse-Diogenes.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
Diogenes the Cynic, a citizen of the world, in a painting by John
William Waterhouse
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tuesday saw the first of a series of reading groups that I’m
organizing at &lt;a href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;CRASSH&lt;/a&gt; on the
subject of &lt;a href="../2012-12-07-crassh-project-speaking-ethically-across-borders" title="CRASSH Project: Speaking Ethically Across Borders"&gt;ethical
conversations across borders&lt;/a&gt;. There will be four sessions this term,
each dealing with a different theme, taking in readings from
anthropology, sociology, philosophy and history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first session, on &lt;em&gt;rooted cosmopolitanisms&lt;/em&gt;, was based on
texts by philosopher Martha Nussbaum and sociologist Bryan Turner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cosmopolitanism is perhaps most frequently used to describe the flows
of people and goods between geographically remote regions. Following
this usage, a ‘cosmopolitan’ is someone who moves with facility between
different regions or cultures. However, the term cosmopolitan is also
used with an ethical force. In this sense, it is the idea that ethical
considerations ought not be limited by geographical boundaries. An
ethical cosmopolitan claims that all persons are equally significant
moral beings, no matter where they are located or where they have come
from. On this view, any ethical attachment for members of one’s own
ethnic group or nation or religion is exercised at the expense of
others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a position that Nussbaum has defended &lt;a href="http://faculty.capebretonu.ca/philosophy/301/pdfs/1%20Patriotism.pdf"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.
However, in the paper we discussed in the reading group, ’&lt;a href="http://www.mitpressjournals.org/doi/abs/10.1162/daed.2008.137.3.78"&gt;Toward
a globally sensitive patriotism&lt;/a&gt;‘ (paywall), she argues that although
the classical conception of cosmopolitanism, which appeals to reason
alone, is right and desirable, it is in incapable of motivating people
and cannot therefore be the basis of an effective politics. What local,
particularistic accounts can provide, which cosmopolitanism, she says,
cannot, is a rich background of historical events, experiences of
landscapes and particular personalities that can play effectively on the
emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nussbaum distinguishes between two forms of love of country. One
form, which she calls patriotism, is focused on leading the subject to
think beyond the self to the good of something greater. Though it
entails particularistic attachments that can come at the cost of global
obligations, Nussbaum believes that patriotism is compatible with
cosmopolitanism and that through its repertoire of local, historically
rich narratives it is capable of evoking altruistic feelings that can be
extended beyond the nation. She gives several examples of patriotic
rhetoric that she believes achieves this goal of harnessing the horse of
visceral attachment to the particular to the carriage of tolerance and
compassion. These include speeches by Martin Luther King and Gandhi,
among others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other form of love of country Nussbaum calls nationalism, this is
based on exclusion of others, and works with shame and disgust.
Nationalism in this sense is incompatible with cosmopolitanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turner’s paper, ’&lt;a href="http://tcs.sagepub.com/content/19/1-2/45.short"&gt;Cosmopolitan
Virtue&lt;/a&gt;‘ (paywall) addresses the problem of human rights. Human
rights are problematic for a number of reasons, including that their
advocates can provide no grounds on which the obligations that must
correspond to rights (i.e. the obligation not to encroach on rights, the
obligation to redress the denial of rights, and so on) might be based.
Turner aims to rescue rights by proposing a cosmopolitan virtue which
would form the basis of such obligations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Nussbaum, Turner thinks that a reason-only approach would prove
ineffective, writing, ‘The idea of global citizenship is probably too
abstract and vague to carry conviction and commitment’ (p. 49). The
solution he proposes harks back to an idea of citizenship that predates
the modern nation-state: ‘…citizenship was originally a product of
Renaissance humanism, in which the ascending order of the state and the
horizontal ordering of citizenship contrasted with the descending theme
of the Church and its hierarchical order of institutionalized grace…
This tradition of citizenship became linked to the norms of civility,
civilization and civil society.’ Becoming a citizen in this sense was a
matter of cultivating virtues, a matter of education or formation. The
virtues were universal ones, but they were learnt in a particular form
and in relation to specific political institutions and traditions. This
is the kind of cosmopolitan virtue that Turner thinks can provide the
obligation that is missing from human rights theory, a virtue that is
based in specific attachments and can therefore command people’s
emotions, but which is aimed at universal goods and avoids exclusion.
The virtues he has in mind emerge as conditions of political debate and
trade, but extend from politeness to care for the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turner also makes a number of other interesting points, in particular
in relation to the universality of the rejection of suffering (a
questionable idea, I think), and about the relation between
cosmopolitanism and irony, but I won’t go into those here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of the question of ethical conversations across borders, I
think the most interesting aspects of these papers are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. The combination of empirical and rationalist approaches. Both
Nussbaum and Turner are committed to a universalist ethics that they see
as being based on reason, but argue that for practical reasons this must
be combined with contingent ethical forms that are necessarily local and
historical. One can imagine other thinkers arriving in the same place
from the opposite direction: a commitment to an empirical approach to
ethics based on actual custom and precedent, a commitment that needs to
be laid aside in international contexts in favour of a first-principles
approach because there is an insufficient body of shared custom among
parties who transact at that level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2. Their arguments raise the question of the spatial relationship of
global ethics and local ethics. Is the cosmopolitan to conceive of
global ethics (i) as being beyond space, something that applies at all
times and in all places where moral persons happen to be, (ii) as being
related to the planet earth as a place, just as local ethics are related
to local places, or (iii) in relation to cosmopolitan spaces such as
international cities, pilgrimage sites, universities and so on, where
citizens of a number of different local polities meet and rub along
together? Neither author really answers this question, though Turner
does talk about the importance of cosmopolitan cities in the development
of cosmopolitan virtue, especially in relation to the ironic detachment
from one’s own tradition that he sees as essential to cosmopolitanism.
Perhaps the aim of Nussbaum’s patriotism is to lead from (i) to (ii)?
Perhaps that would depend on the emergence of prominent participatory
political institutions at the global level. Will the increasing
importance of international cities lead from (i) to (iii), or from (iii)
to (ii)? This issue — the location of the global — is relevant to any
scheme that attempts to connect local and universal ethical
considerations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="references"&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 13px;"&gt;Nussbaum, M. 2011. Patriotism and
cosmopolitanism. In &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Cosmopolitanism Reader&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 13px;"&gt; (eds) D. Held &amp;amp; G. W. Brown, 155–178.
Polity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 13px;"&gt;Nussbaum, M. 2008. Toward a globally
sensitive patriotism. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Daedalus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;137&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 13px;"&gt;, 78–93.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 13px;"&gt;Turner, B. 2002. Cosmopolitan Virtue,
Globalization and Patriotism. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theory, Culture &amp;amp;
Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;19&lt;/strong&gt;, 45–63.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Bryan Turner"></category><category term="cosmopolitanism"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="Gandhi"></category><category term="Martha Nussbaum"></category><category term="Martin Luther King"></category><category term="philosophy"></category><category term="sociology"></category></entry><entry><title>Alastair Macintyre on the moral-instrumental division of the modern world</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/alastair-macintyre-on-the-moral-instrumental-division-of-the-modern-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-15:/alastair-macintyre-on-the-moral-instrumental-division-of-the-modern-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am reading Alasdair MacIntyre’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0715636405/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0715636405&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=210d14-21"&gt;After
Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1981), and I’ve just come
across a passage that is related to my recent argument about the
problems of the use of the concept of neoliberalism in anthropology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument was that academic advocates …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am reading Alasdair MacIntyre’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0715636405/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0715636405&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=210d14-21"&gt;After
Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1981), and I’ve just come
across a passage that is related to my recent argument about the
problems of the use of the concept of neoliberalism in anthropology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument was that academic advocates of neoliberalism and
academic critics of it share a view of the world, for all their apparent
disagreement, in which all action is &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; moral &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;
instrumental. I argued that this was part of a long argument in western
thought that took the division for granted and in which the problematic
was what the proper balance between the two spheres of life should be,
and that neither position can adequately comprehend forms of moral life
in which effective instrumentality is considered to have intrinsic
ethical value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacIntyre’s book historicizes this very distinction, attributing its
emergence to the attempt of Enlightenment thinkers to justify morality,
and looks at historical forms of virtue in which the good and the
effective were unified. MacIntyre’s target is not, of course,
‘neoliberalism-ism’, but a theory of morality he describes as emotivism.
He argues that emotivism dominates moral thought in the contemporary
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotivism, according to Macintyre, is premised on the division of the
social world into,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…a realm of the organizational in which ends are taken to be given
and are not available for rational scrutiny and a realm of the personal
in which judgment and debate about values are central factors, but in
which no rational social resolution of issues is available…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…debates are often staged in terms of a supposed opposition between
individualism and collectivism, each appearing in a variety of doctrinal
forms. On the one side there appear the self-defined protagonists of
individual liberty, on the other the self-defined protagonists of
planning and regulation, of the goods which are available through
bureaucratic organization. But in fact what is crucial is that on which
the contending parties agree, namely that there are only two alternative
modes of social life open to us, one in which the free and arbitrary
choices of individuals are sovereign and one in which the bureaucracy is
sovereign, precisely so it may limit the free and arbitrary choices if
individuals (p. 34f).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Alasdair MacIntyre"></category><category term="emotivism"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Neoliberal is henceforth dead to me</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/neoliberal-is-henceforth-dead-to-me.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-14T16:53:31+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-14:/neoliberal-is-henceforth-dead-to-me.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Theo Kyriakides (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bio_karneia"&gt;@bio_karneia&lt;/a&gt;), who was
present at the &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;GDAT debate on
neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt; for alerting me to a post by Kathleen Fitzpatrick of
Pomona College. She writes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come to despise the term “neoliberal,” to the extent that I’d
really like to see it stricken from academic …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Theo Kyriakides (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bio_karneia"&gt;@bio_karneia&lt;/a&gt;), who was
present at the &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;GDAT debate on
neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt; for alerting me to a post by Kathleen Fitzpatrick of
Pomona College. She writes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come to despise the term “neoliberal,” to the extent that I’d
really like to see it stricken from academic vocabularies everywhere.
It’s less that I have a problem with the actual critique that the term
is meant to levy than with the utterly sloppy and nearly always casually
derisive way in which the term is of late being thrown about. 1
“Neoliberal” is hardly ever used these days to point to instances of the
elevation of market values above all others — it’s used to tar anything
that has anything to do with any market realities whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the rest here: &lt;a href="https://kfitz.info/neoliberal/"&gt;“Neoliberal” | Planned
Obsolescence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="https://kfitz.info/more-on-that-word/"&gt;later post&lt;/a&gt;,
she says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;like “bourgeois” or “reactionary” or any number of other such terms,
I have too often of late heard “neoliberal” deployed as an insult by
people on the left against &lt;em&gt;other people on the left&lt;/em&gt;. It’s the
classic circular firing squad of ideological purity, and it makes me
nuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Kathleen Fitzpatrick"></category><category term="neoliberal university"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category></entry><entry><title>CRASSH Project: Speaking Ethically Across Borders</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/crassh-project-speaking-ethically-across-borders.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T09:54:37+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-07:/crassh-project-speaking-ethically-across-borders.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am currently a research fellow at &lt;a href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;CRASSH&lt;/a&gt;, the Centre for Research
in the Arts, Social Sciences and Humanities, at &lt;a href="http://www.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;Cambridge University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’m working on is an interdisciplinary project on
‘Speaking Ethically Across Borders’. Right now I’m planning a reading
group on the topic …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am currently a research fellow at &lt;a href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;CRASSH&lt;/a&gt;, the Centre for Research
in the Arts, Social Sciences and Humanities, at &lt;a href="http://www.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;Cambridge University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’m working on is an interdisciplinary project on
‘Speaking Ethically Across Borders’. Right now I’m planning a reading
group on the topic for next term. The outline is below, together with
some sample readings. If anyone has any suggestions for good readings on
this theme, from any discipline, please let me know by email or in the
comments below. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, this is related to my last post: the conversations I am
interested in for this project could be seen as self-conscious attempts
to overcome potential conversations at cross-purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="speaking-ethically-across-borders"&gt;Speaking ethically across
borders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A conversation between Western Christendom and the Mongol Empire: Pope Innocent IV sends a mission to Central Asia, carrying one of a series of letters that were exchanged between the pontiffs and the Mongol khans in the thirteenth century. (Source: Wikipedia)" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/AscelinOfCremone.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;A conversation between Western
Christendom and the Mongol Empire:&lt;br/&gt;
Pope Innocent IV sends a mission to Central Asia, carrying one of a
series of letters that were exchanged between the pontiffs and the
Mongol khans in the thirteenth century. (Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychologists such as Judith Smetana have argued that the distinction
between moral rule and social convention is innate and universal. That
may be so, but knowing that there is a difference is not the same as
knowing where the line can be drawn that divides the two. When we are in
familiar settings, the differences between tradition, habit, and
pragmatic efficiency on the one hand, and ethical considerations about
value and duty are frequently elided: there are a limited number of
given, concrete ways of living life, and most of our choices will be
made from among them. Even innovations justified on moral grounds will
silently incorporate much that is conventional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when people speak ethically across regional boundaries, they must
face the problem of finding ways to render the ethics of different
regions commensurate, either by translating local, thick ethical
practices of one or both sides into the thin common currency of some
universalist morality, or by claiming that, in so far as the essentials
are concerned, what appear to be quite different values or practices are
in fact compatible. In either case, there is a need to agree on a place
to draw the line dividing universal or shared essence from contingent
cultural convention, to decide whether it is the specific practices that
are valued, or only the underlying principle, only their effects, or
some combination of these. This makes these conversations an ideal site
for scholars interested in understanding moral reasoning and its
relation to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="possible-examples-of-conversations-across-borders"&gt;Possible
examples of conversations across borders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A Jesuit in Confucian ceremonial robes during the period of the Confucian Rites Controversy - rival claims to moral authority between rival regional powers with cosmopolitan aspirations. Source: Wikipedia." src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/NicolasTrigaultInChineseCostume.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;A Jesuit in Confucian ceremonial robes
during the period of the Confucian Rites Controversy - rival claims to
moral authority between rival regional powers with cosmopolitan
aspirations. Source: Wikipedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the universalization of local ethical traditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conversely, the vernacularization of cosmopolitan ethics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;civilizing and proselytizing missions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempts of diaspora populations to adapt the ethical culture of the
contemporary, historical, or imagined home region to life in a variety
of different moral environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempts to preserve a regional moral order in the face of
modernization by separating &lt;em&gt;ethos&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (many
fascinating examples to draw here from East Asia, including the May
Fourth Movement and Deng Xiao Ping’s ‘Socialism with Chinese
Characteristics’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sample-bibliography"&gt;Sample Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bakken, Borge. 2000. The Exemplary Society: Human Improvement, Social
Control, and the Dangers of Modernity in China. Oxford: Oxford
University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buckser, A. 2008. “Cultural Change and the Meanings of Belief in
Jewish Copenhagen.” Social Analysis 52 (1): 39–55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humphrey, C. 2007. “Alternative Freedoms.” Proceedings of the
American Philosophical Society 151 (1): 1–10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laidlaw, James. 2010. Ethical Traditions in Question: Diaspora
Jainism and the Environmental and Animal Liberation Movements. In
Ethical Life in South Asia. Edited by Anand Pandian and Daud Ali.
Bloomington: Indiana University Press: 61-80&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nussbaum, Martha. 2011. “Patriotism and Cosmopolitanism.” In &lt;em&gt;The
Cosmopolitanism Reader&lt;/em&gt;, ed. David Held and Garrett Wallace Brown,
155-178. Cambridge: Polity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roy, Olivier. 2006. “Islam in the West or Western Islam? The
Disconnect of Religion and Culture.” Hedgehog Review 8 (1/2): 127.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rapport, N. (1998) The potential of human rights in a post-cultural
world. Social Anthropology. 6/3: 381-388.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sheldon Pollock. 1998. “The Cosmopolitan Vernacular.” The Journal of
Asian Studies 57 (1): 6-37.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schmieder, F. 2000. “Cum Hora Undecima: The Incorporation of Asia
into the Orbis Christianus.” In Christianizing Peoples and Converting
Individuals, ed. Guyda Armstrong and Ian N. Wood, 259–65. Turnhout:
Brepols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turner, B.S. 2002. “Cosmopolitan Virtue, Globalization and
Patriotism.” Theory, Culture &amp;amp; Society 19 (1-2): 45.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="CRASSH"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="inter-disciplinarity"></category></entry><entry><title>Cross-cultural conversations at cross-purposes</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/cross-cultural-conversations-at-cross-purposes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-05T19:13:32+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T09:52:56+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-05:/cross-cultural-conversations-at-cross-purposes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument in the recent &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;neoliberalism
debate&lt;/a&gt; was that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;evidence of discontent about any aspect, be it ever so narrow, of
what have been identified as neoliberal transformations is taken,
without further justification, as a rejection of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the
phenomena that have been so identified&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument in the recent &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;neoliberalism
debate&lt;/a&gt; was that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;evidence of discontent about any aspect, be it ever so narrow, of
what have been identified as neoliberal transformations is taken,
without further justification, as a rejection of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the
phenomena that have been so identified&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point was that just because lots of people in different countries
are critics of, say, structural adjustment programmes, we cannot leap to
the conclusion that they share the same conception of the state and
civil society and all agree on the proper balance of power and resources
between the two; their motivations and assumptions might be quite
different in each case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a formal problem of cross-cultural description or comparison:
the conversation at cross-purposes. We recognize something familiar in
other people’s statements, and rush to fill in the rest from our own
common-sense ideas, which may be quite different. My favourite example
of this is one that operates in both directions — a reciprocal
conversation at cross-purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="self-cultivation-jesus-christ-and-christ-jesus"&gt;Self-Cultivation,
Jesus Christ, and Christ Jesus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian missionaries, mainly Americans, operate in China in spite
of a prohibition on missionary activity. Their message tends to be the
&lt;strong&gt;rules-based&lt;/strong&gt; version of modern Evangelism that has taken
so much of the world by storm over the past 30 years: don’t drink, don’t
smoke, don’t gamble, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christians I have met in villages in the north of China, or people
who were &lt;em&gt;interested in Christianity&lt;/em&gt; as they would invariably
put it, were, it seemed to me, used to thinking about religious practice
quite differently: as being aimed at a gradual process of
&lt;strong&gt;self-cultivation&lt;/strong&gt;. Like an impressive athletic feat —
such as running a marathon — this is something that is easy for anyone
to admire. But to participate — that takes a certain degree of
commitment, free time and self-confidence. Again and again, when I asked
people if they were Christian they would self-deprecatingly say that
they knew little about it, that they were busy, but planned to start
being a Christian in the future, perhaps when the harvest was in and
there was less farm work to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in China researching the revival of Buddhism in Mongolian
areas, and Buddhists — or people who were interested in Buddhism — would
often tell me similar things: Buddhism is a deep culture that is very
powerful, but not many people are capable of putting it into practice,
they were happy being relatively passive admirers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the village Christians do practise, they see the purpose of
self-denial not as the fulfilment of an imperative duty, but rather as a
technology through which they will gain good fortune through hard work.
This means that it the practices taught by missionaries, sometimes long
ago, tend to drift into more extreme forms of asceticism. For instance,
in one village I was told that a religion of Christ Jesus had emerged to
challenge the established religion of Jesus Christ. The followers of
Christ Jesus interpreted the injunction to pray often as an esoteric
teaching involving sitting absolutely still for hours with a wet towel
on one’s head— a dangerous as well as an uncomfortable proposition in
windy, icy Inner Mongolia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="guilty-buddhists"&gt;Guilty Buddhists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reciprocal part of this conversation at cross-purposes is the
adoption of Buddhism in many non-Asian contexts in which religion,
especially monotheisms, tends to be thought of as a revelation of moral
duty — that is, as part of a system of &lt;strong&gt;rule-based
morality&lt;/strong&gt; — rather than a set of technologies for
self-development. The corollary of duty is guilt. If what I have read is
representative, Western Buddhist leaders seem to be occupied quite a lot
of the time with advising their followers not to feel guilty if they
miss out on a meditation session (just google &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=don't+feel+guilty+for+not+meditating"&gt;‘don’t
feel guilty for not meditating’&lt;/a&gt; to see what I mean), or if they
cannot resist eating meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This conversation at cross-purposes is facilitated by near-enough
‘religion’ concepts — false friends that make communication easy, even
intuitive. The confusion that arises is evident in the accusations of
hypocrisy, or justifications of apparent hypocrisy, that arose in early
anthropological studies of Buddhism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that a Buddhist who does not follow Buddhist precepts is
hypocritical, among my Inner Mongolian Buddhist friends at least, would
be as inappropriate as accusing a Manchester United fan of being
hypocritical for failing to play in the Premier League. On the other
side, to my Chinese and Mongolian informants, foreign religionists —
mainly those missionaries — often seem arrogant because they imagine
that they themselves are capable right now, without any preparation, let
alone indefinite deferment, of participating in all the practices that
are commanded of them by their God. (I’m not making a point about
Chinese people getting Christianity wrong, or non-Asians getting
Buddhism wrong — I don’t have a horse in those races, I’m just
interested in the formal problem.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-request"&gt;A request&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some time I have been toying with the idea of compiling a
compendium of cross-cultural conversations at cross-purposes, or
cross-cultural faux amis / &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_friend"&gt;false friends&lt;/a&gt;. It
would include those situations in which concepts on each side of the
conversation are different enough to produce disagreements or confusion,
but similar enough that it may be unclear where the disagreement
originates. Please let me know in the comments or by email if you know
of any good examples for my collection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Buddhism"></category><category term="China"></category><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="conversations at cross-purposes"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="Inner Mongolia"></category><category term="missionaries"></category><category term="self-cultivation"></category></entry><entry><title>GDAT 2012: Debating “neoliberalism”</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-05T13:49:55+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-05:/gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Saturday I had the pleasure of taking part in &lt;a href="http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/disciplines/socialanthropology/research/gdat/"&gt;GDAT&lt;/a&gt;,
an annual debate on anthropological theory hosted by Manchester
University. GDAT, the Group for Debates in Anthropological Theory, was
started in the late 80s by Tim Ingold, and has been organized and
chaired more recently by Soumhya Venkatesan. This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Saturday I had the pleasure of taking part in &lt;a href="http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/disciplines/socialanthropology/research/gdat/"&gt;GDAT&lt;/a&gt;,
an annual debate on anthropological theory hosted by Manchester
University. GDAT, the Group for Debates in Anthropological Theory, was
started in the late 80s by Tim Ingold, and has been organized and
chaired more recently by Soumhya Venkatesan. This was the third GDAT I
have attended and I think it’s a brilliant institution. People come from
all over the country, and the discussion is always highly engaged and
critical in the best sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year’s motion was: &lt;em&gt;The concept of neoliberalism has become
an obstacle to the anthropological understanding of the twenty-first
century&lt;/em&gt;. James Laidlaw was proposing, I seconded, and Thomas
Hylland Eriksen and Keir Martin opposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of the concept of ‘neoliberalism’ has been a bugbear of mine
since a conference I attended in 2009. Every panel I attended had at
least one paper on neoliberalism, but each seemed to be talking about
quite different, even contradictory, things — the neoliberal tag seemed
to add nothing. Or worse, it seemed portentously to invoke a whole
global theory as a background explanation without doing the work of
showing how ‘global forces’ are actually linked to or expressed in the
sort of ‘local’ settings the speakers were talking about. It has become
a kind of disciplinary common sense reinforced by a smug sense of shared
moral indignation and that is reason enough to question its
usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the speeches will be available on the University of Manchester
website soon, and I understand a recording of the debate will be made
available as a podcast. Eventually, the whole thing, with a
transcription of the questions following the speeches, will be published
in &lt;a href="http://coa.sagepub.com/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critique of
Anthropology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In the meantime, I’ll be happy to send anyone
who’s interested a copy of my speech — here’s a snippet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discourse of academic critics of neoliberalism is nothing but the
discourse of the academic proponents of neoliberalism—but with the signs
reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither side invented the categories it works with. This disagreement
is simply the latest battle in a long, long war in western thought about
the proper balance of the moral and the instrumental spheres of life.
One side in this argument has always argued that the sphere of economic
rationality should be carefully constrained in order to preserve moral
life from its taint. The other side has always argued that more amoral
selfishness in the short term will produce the optimum outcome for all
in the end and is therefore, only apparently paradoxically, the more
moral course of action. What both sides take for granted is the
fundamental division of the moral from the instrumental. (If the concept
of ‘ontology’ were not just as compromised as ‘neoliberalism’, one might
want to deploy it here.) The use of the concept of neoliberalism in
anthropological writing has been little more than an excuse to rehearse
this old and essentially parochial argument, in a way that appears to
mobilize ethnographic evidence but in fact precludes the possibility of
learning anything new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We lost, horribly. I got a good laugh with that line about ‘ontology’
though…talk about professional in-jokes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE (31 Jan 2013): The audio recording of the debate is now
available &lt;a href="https://www.podchaser.com/podcasts/talking-anthropology-115090/episodes/ta45-gdat1-neoliberalism-5315861"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="debate"></category><category term="gdat"></category><category term="‘James Laidlaw’"></category><category term="‘Keir Martin’"></category><category term="manchester"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category><category term="‘Thomas Hylland Eriksen’"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolution and Religion Part III</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion-part-iii.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-11-18T20:09:45+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-11-18:/evolution-and-religion-part-iii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Michael,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for taking the time to engage with me earlier. Sorry
that this is a bit of a long reply…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your comment you note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the fundamental questions remains: Why are only “religious”
communities able to augment this in-group cooperation not, say,
political parties or sport clubs …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Michael,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again for taking the time to engage with me earlier. Sorry
that this is a bit of a long reply…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In your comment you note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the fundamental questions remains: Why are only “religious”
communities able to augment this in-group cooperation not, say,
political parties or sport clubs?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certainly an interesting question, and one that is not
affected by the objections in my previous post, but I do have some
reservations on this count too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="comparing-like-with-like"&gt;1. Comparing like with like&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we can address the question, we need to make sure we’re
comparing like with like. From your &lt;a href="http://www.scilogs.com/nature-of-faith/its-about-fertility-stupid-the-evolutionary-adaptivity-of-religion/"&gt;original
post&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found many religious traditions that were able to attain high
levels of fertility throughout the generations. But in sharp empirical
contrast, we didn’t find a single non-religious community, movement or
population that was able to retain at least replacement level (two
births per woman) for a century!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way you put this explicitly rules out any kind of organization
that is not involved in baby making (“two births per woman”). That’s
fair enough, as you’re interested in evolution, which ultimately depends
on differential reproductive advantage. But doing this also means that
you cannot legitimately take such organizations as sports clubs as
secular equivalents of religious groups in your comparisons. Of course
tennis clubs can’t achieve two births per woman — they don’t (as far as
I know) admit members by birth! This has no necessary or causal relation
to religiosity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignleft" style="width: 205px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.medals.org.uk/mongolia/mongolia020.htm"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mongolian Medal: ‘Aldart Ekh’ – Renowned Mother, First Class" src="https://i0.wp.com/www.medals.org.uk/mongolia/images/mongolia028.jpg?resize=205%2C250" title="Mongolian Medal: 'Aldart Ekh' -- Renowned Mother, First Class"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
Mongolian Medal: ‘Aldart Ekh’ — Renowned Mother, First Class
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make a comparison in terms of replacement by birth — the
comparison that would allow us to reach the conclusion that religious
communities have an advantage over non-religious ones in terms of
reproduction — &lt;strong&gt;we’d have to find non-religious organizations
that *did* base membership at least in part on reproduction and
birth.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to non-reproduction related groups such as sports clubs
and political parties, it is hard to think of many examples. Why that
should be the case is an interesting question in itself — I’ll consider
that below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps some modernist nationalisms (especially those allied to
eugenic policies?), or ethnic groups without strong religious
affiliation (some national minorities in China?) would fit the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are good examples of the former — I’m thinking especially of
the Hero Mother campaigns in the Soviet Union and other Communist
countries, and these did achieve very high birth rates. Some people have
argued that Stalinism had religious characteristics — maybe so, but it
was certainly not interested in non-empirical agents
(i.e. ‘religiosity’, in your terms). When I first went to Ulanbaatar in
2002, many people still proudly declared themselves ‘materialist’ when I
asked them about religion! These national movements really did achieve
huge population growth. Admittedly, it was not sustained over much more
than two generations….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-historical-question"&gt;2. The historical question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…Which brings us to my second reservation: the historical depth, or
lack of it, of non-religious organizations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we were going to make a generalization about the relative
reproductive success of religious and non-religious communities, one
that is to hold good across evolutionary time, we would need to have a
decent number of examples of both kinds of community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are good reasons to think it is impossible to find a sufficient
sample of non-religious, membership-by-reproduction communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason is the historical novelty of secularism. The idea of
having communities or institutions that exclude religiosity (on your
definition) simply does not have a long history. It is an idea that had
its origins in the Enlightenment or the development of the nation state
(see Talal Asad, Charles Taylor — refs below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more general account might give a role to the modern phenomenon of
‘purification’. Early anthropologists were fascinated by the fact that
the institutions they studied among ‘natives’ in colonial contexts
around the world could not be pigeonholed into one of the major
categories that we use to understand modern society, such as politics,
economics, kinship, religion and so on. For example, an annual meeting
between villages might involve arrangements for marriages (kinship),
exchanges of goods (economics), offerings to ancestors (religion), and
alliances (politics). Marcel Mauss called this a total institution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, modern societies are characterized by an attempt to
purify institutions so that they only perform one kind of role…if your
economic institution also performs kinship functions, that’s called
nepotism! If your political institution performs commercial functions,
corruption! Bruno Latour has argued that this work of purification is
more rhetorical than actual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the evidence seems to suggest that secular communities in
general were either very rare or non-existent (on a broad or narrow
definition of secularism, respectively) until the modern
period.&lt;/strong&gt; This explanation accounts parsimoniously for your being
unable to find any long-lived communities defined by their exclusion of
religion throughout history — there simply weren’t any such communities
until relatively recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the lack of longstanding communities of this kind were instead
down to relative reproductive disadvantage, am I wrong in thinking that
we should see a long history of ephemeral secular birth-related
communities that die out quickly? Can you name any one such community
dating to before 1600? The examples you give of communities that did not
prosper are defined by their &lt;em&gt;religious&lt;/em&gt; characteristics — they
don’t appear to be secular in any sense (Shakers, ancient Pagans).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it may be too soon to say whether secular birth-related
communities will prove to be successful. It may continue to be difficult
to say: the reason such communities are &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; likely to be rare
may be that the modern practice of purification that I outlined above
tends to militate against birth/kinship functions being mixed up with
other functions. Such a mixture would be a necessary condition of
recognizing a community as anything other than a kinship group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conclusion"&gt;3. Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If my reservations about comparisons before the modern period and
comparisons are justified, then what remains to be explained is the
apparent reproductive advantage of religiously defined groups over other
groups &lt;em&gt;in the modern period&lt;/em&gt; — accepting your example of
Switzerland as representative and unproblematic. The relation of this
phenomenon to religiosity, on your definition, was the subject of my
previous two posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;References&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asad, Talal. 2003. &lt;em&gt;Formations of the Secular&lt;/em&gt;. Stanford
University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Latour, Bruno. 1993. &lt;em&gt;We Have Never Been Modern&lt;/em&gt;. Harvard
University Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mauss, Marcel. 1970. &lt;em&gt;The Gift&lt;/em&gt;. Taylor &amp;amp; Francis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taylor, Charles. 2007. &lt;em&gt;A Secular Age&lt;/em&gt;. Harvard University
Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Bruno Latour"></category><category term="Charles Taylor"></category><category term="China"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="Marcel Mauss"></category><category term="Michael Blume"></category><category term="Mongolia"></category><category term="Soviet Union"></category><category term="Talal Asad"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolution and Religion Part II</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion-part-ii.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-11-18T11:15:40+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-11-18:/evolution-and-religion-part-ii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 220px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Robertson_Smith"&gt;&lt;img alt="William Robertson Smith" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/WilliamRobertsonSmith.jpg" title="William Robertson Smith"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
William Robertson Smith (source: Wikipedia)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a reply to &lt;del&gt;Martin&lt;/del&gt; Michael Blume’s &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/#comment-18"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt;
to my previous &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, which
was itself was a comment on his blog on &lt;a href="http://www.scilogs.com/nature-of-faith/its-about-fertility-stupid-the-evolutionary-adaptivity-of-religion/"&gt;www.scilogs.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;del&gt;
Martin
&lt;/del&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael — Thanks for the links (reproduced below) and for engaging
with my comment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read those …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 220px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Robertson_Smith"&gt;&lt;img alt="William Robertson Smith" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/WilliamRobertsonSmith.jpg" title="William Robertson Smith"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
William Robertson Smith (source: Wikipedia)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a reply to &lt;del&gt;Martin&lt;/del&gt; Michael Blume’s &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/#comment-18"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt;
to my previous &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, which
was itself was a comment on his blog on &lt;a href="http://www.scilogs.com/nature-of-faith/its-about-fertility-stupid-the-evolutionary-adaptivity-of-religion/"&gt;www.scilogs.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;del&gt;
Martin
&lt;/del&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael — Thanks for the links (reproduced below) and for engaging
with my comment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read those two papers now –they are thought provoking and
contain some great lines (“evolutionary theorists brought up far more
scientific arguments — but committed believers in supernatural agents
brought up far more children”–love it!), but I don’t think they really
answer my initial objection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On page 118 of the Reproductive Benefits paper, you write (I’ve added
emphasis and labels in square brackets):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;” [1] Religiosity, understood as *believing* in supernatural guidance
and surveillance of all parties involved, evolved (and evolves) as a
biological and highly successful solution. [2] Humans who are *members*
of religious communities show statistically higher motivations towards
marriage, children and family values, more cooperative orientation and
finally higher reproductive success than their secular
contemporaries”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am questioning is the relation between religiosity as defined
in [1] and the membership of religious communities referred to in [2].
You draw conclusions about ‘religiosity’ (i.e., belief, on your
definition — I’ll use this word with that force from now on) on the
basis of data about religious affiliation, taking the latter to be
indicative of the former. It is clear from the social scientific
literature on religion that the link between these things is uncertain
to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this in any way invalidates your observations about religious
&lt;em&gt;communities&lt;/em&gt; and reproduction. But if I am right the following
objections follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="over-interpretation-of-the-data"&gt;1. Over-interpretation of the
data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be over-interpreting the census data in making the leap from
affiliation to traditional communities with religious associations to
religiosity, on your terms. (I am dubious about the methodology of the
World Values Survey for many of the same reasons by the way, but it’s a
long time since I’ve looked at it so I can’t comment in detail.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave Day’s study as an example in my post because her work directly
addresses the difference between people’s ‘superempirical’ behaviour and
thought and their response to questions about religious affiliation in a
national census.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the question of the discrepancy between belief and
affiliation has been a constant theme in social scientific studies of
religion since at least the end of the 19C and the work of William
Robertson Smith (ref below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason this question is of enduring interest is that it confounds
the expectations of modern models of religion that are basically
Protestant or post-reformation in nature, especially the expectation
that religion is above all about a personal, interior relationship to
God and the holy, that a particular tradition of worship is associated
with particular institutions and so on. Even in countries (such as the
UK) where this model might be expected to apply most strongly (because
for centuries it has been a model of what religion &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be
like), ethnographic work (such as Day’s) shows consistently that the
boundaries between beliefs and boundaries between religious affiliation
are frequently do not line up in the way the model would predict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anachronism"&gt;2. Anachronism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it were shown that the association between religious
affiliation and religious belief were sound for modern populations, your
conclusions project this combination back throughout history and
prehistory. If we didn’t know anything about changing configurations of
religious behaviour, then that might be a reasonable move. However,
there’s plenty of evidence that the idea of a discrete religion that
comprises a combination of {(i) an exclusive, systematic religious
doctrine + (ii) exclusive use of certain religious practices + (iii) a
specific and exclusive religious affiliation} is a relatively recent
invention that is even now by no means the norm, and which requires a
great deal of policing to make sure that people defined by any one of
these characteristics are also defined by the other two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you have evidence that contradicts the consensus in the
literature, then explaining the evolutionary origins and persistence of
religiosity throughout human existence in terms of the reproductive
advantage it bestows on religious communities may be like seeking the
explanation for the origins and persistence of language over 100s of
thousands of years in terms of its essential role in hip hop. Doing this
would not only misrepresent the nature of language over the long term,
it would also make hip-hop seem like a universal and transhistorical
phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By eliding the difference between religious affiliation and religious
belief, and drawing the conclusion that the combination is an
evolutionary adaptation, you give the impression that religion in this
sense is universal and transhistorical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t, by the way, have any axe to grind (some social scientists
do) whatsoever on the question of human universals — I think it’s
obvious that there is such a thing as human nature and that we ought to
try to understand it, but it’s important that in doing that we do take
into account everything we know about human variation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More to come!…UPDATE: &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion-part-iii/" title="Evolution and Religion Part III"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE 5 Dec 2012: Don’t know anything about the quality/provenance
of this research, but if it’s right it’s grist to my mill: &lt;a href="http://www.religiondispatches.org/dispatches/guest_bloggers/6648/%E2%80%98nones%E2%80%99_&amp;amp;ne%3b_nonreligious_%7c_/"&gt;‘Nones’
≠ Nonreligious&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;References&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was the first major work to question the link between belief
and communal affiliation:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smith, William Robertson. 1889. &lt;em&gt;Lectures on the Religion of the
Semites&lt;/em&gt;. Edinburgh: Adam and Charles Black.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These articles by Talal Asad criticise the tendency of other
scholars of religion to assume that personal, internal psychological
experience, such as belief, is central to religion, thus universalizing
certain aspects of contemporary Christian experience:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asad, Talal. 1983. “Anthropological Conceptions of Religion:
Reflections on Geertz.” &lt;em&gt;Man: The Journal of the Royal
Anthropological Institute&lt;/em&gt; NS 18: 237–259.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asad, T. 2001. “Reading a modern classic: W. C. Smith’s The Meaning
and End of Religion.” &lt;em&gt;History of Religions&lt;/em&gt; 40 (3):
205–222.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This book describes the process through which leaders of the
newly named ‘World Religions’ remade their traditions in the image of
post-Reformation Christianity in the 19C:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masuzawa, Tomoko. 2005. &lt;em&gt;The Invention of World Religions : or,
How European Universalism Was Preserved in the Language of
Pluralism&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago, Ill.: London : University of Chicago
Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article describes a similar process in the Russian Reupblic
of Altai, where Protestant missionaries failed to garner many converts
to Christianity, but succeeded in spreading the idea of exclusive
religiosity, in a situation in which people had previously been
religiously promiscuous:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broz, Ludek. 2009. &lt;a href="http://www.academia.edu/1035385/CONVERSION_TO_RELIGION_NEGOTIATING_CONTINUITY_AND_DISCONTINUITY_IN_CONTEMPORARY_ALTAI"&gt;“Conversion
to Religion?”&lt;/a&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Conversion After Socialism: Disruptions,
Modernisms and Technologies of Faith in the Former Soviet Union&lt;/em&gt;,
ed. Mathijs Pelkmans. Berghahn Books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article has a good review of the ethnographic literature on
belief, much of which is concerned with explaining the common
discrepancy between religious affiliation, religious practice and
religious belief:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lindquist, Galina, and Simon Coleman. 2008. “Introduction: Against
Belief?” &lt;em&gt;Social Analysis&lt;/em&gt; 52 (1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the dangers of drawing universal conclusions about human
nature that inadvertently incorporate specific characteristics of those
populations for which data is easy to come by:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heine, Stephen, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://cmbconference2012.org/the-weirdest-people-in-the-world-the-inductive-challenge-for-psychology/"&gt;The
weirdest people in the world: The inductive challenge for
psychology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (conference abstract)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="Michael Blume"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="social science"></category><category term="Talal Asad"></category><category term="William Robertson Smith"></category></entry><entry><title>Evolution and Religion</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-11-16T09:58:29+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-11-16:/evolution-and-religion.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The explanatory power of evolutionary theory is clear. However, these
days, people seem to rush to evolutionary explanations for all sorts of
real and perceived human behaviours. The danger of doing this is that in
going straight to the question of the origins of what we’re trying to
understand …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The explanatory power of evolutionary theory is clear. However, these
days, people seem to rush to evolutionary explanations for all sorts of
real and perceived human behaviours. The danger of doing this is that in
going straight to the question of the origins of what we’re trying to
understand, we fail to put in the effort to adequately study the nature
of the phenomenon, or even to establish satisfactorily that the
phenomenon is real. As a result, it’s all too easy for commonsensical
assumptions and misapprehensions to get incorporated into the story. And
when it comes to human behaviour, things are often more complicated and
more variable than common sense would lead us to expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="its-probably-about-affiliation-and-endogamy-michael"&gt;It’s
probably about affiliation and endogamy, Michael!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a particularly common problem, in my view, in evolutionary
studies of religion, and I’ve just read a blog post that’s a case in
point. In &lt;a href="http://www.scilogs.com/nature-of-faith/its-about-fertility-stupid-the-evolutionary-adaptivity-of-religion/"&gt;It’s
about Fertility, stupid! The Evolutionary Adaptivity of Religion&lt;/a&gt;’,
Michael Blume claims that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Religiosity (defined as behavior towards superempircal agents) is
today clearly adaptive: Members of competitive religious communities are
building stronger families with more offspring worldwide as their
secular neighbours of the same education and income levels. This is
observable in empirical studies, censusses worldwide, as well as in case
studies (i.e. Amish, Hutterites, Mormons, Orthodox Jews). In contrast,
non-religious populations and those religious communities who do not
build and support families inevitably succumb to cultural evolution
(i.e. late Greek and Roman Polytheism, Gnostic groups, the Shakers) and
are replaced by demographically successful religious competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blume’s interpretation of the empirical data depends on the premise
that affiliation to these groups as revealed in, say, censuses, is a
reliable indicator of religiosity, on his definition. But there is a
good deal of social scientific evidence that shows that this cannot be
taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give just one example, a great study of belief in contemporary
northern England published last year by Abby Day (&lt;a href="http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/ReligionTheology/SociologyofReligion/?view=usa&amp;amp;ci=9780199577873"&gt;Believing
in Belonging&lt;/a&gt;) shows that ideas about belonging and ideas about the
supernatural can be surprisingly independent of each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years now, church attendance in Britain has been in decline, and
sociologists have debated what this means. Some argued it was a sign of
‘secularization’–an inevitable loss of religious belief associated with
the modernization and rationalization of society. Others argued that it
was a result of individualization, and that Britons continued to believe
in God, but now preferred to practise their religion quietly on their
own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day’s study, which was based on interviews in Yorkshire villages,
found a more complex picture. Her interviewees turned out to be quite
polarized in their views. Some of them–she calls them
‘theocentrics’–place God at the centre of their lives, as a source of
moral value, a cause of everyday events, and an object of their
attention and affections. Others–Day calls these ‘anthropocentrics’–see
no place for God, and instead locate value and meaning in their
relationships with other humans. Anthropocentrics take a dim view of
theocentrism and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An everyday story of small town intolerance, then, and perhaps no
surprise. So why did Day not just call her two groups ‘religious’, and
‘secularists’ instead of inventing two new terms? Well, it turned out
that of the respondents who identified themselves as Christian, about
half were anthropocentric, and many of those were assertively atheist.
Many of those self-identified Christians said they were hostile to the
idea of institutional religion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, many of those who identified with no religion told Day
that they prayed, believed in fate or some kind of providence, had seen
ghosts or had communicated with deceased relatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his article, Blume mentions that his work was partly based on
census data. It’s worth noting that most of Day’s Christians, including
the ‘anthropocentric’ atheists, said that they had answered ‘Christian’
in response to the religious affiliation question in the 2001 UK census
(the first modern UK census to include a religion question).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day’s work shows that being associated with, or feeling a sense of
identity and belonging in respect of, a ‘religious community’ is quite a
different thing to ‘religiosity (defined as behavior towards
superempircal agents)’. Religiosity is neither exclusive to, nor
universal among, members of ‘competitive religious communities’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, unless the empirical data are sufficient to distinguish
between belonging and believing, there is no reason to suppose that
religiosity, on Blume’s definition, has anything to do with the
increased reproductive success Blume finds for religious communities
through history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there is a simpler explanation at hand. Many of the
historical and contemporary religious groups that we identify as such
combine a self-conscious sense of identity with a greater or lesser
degree of endogamy (marriage within the group) and they tend to value
having and bringing up children and the relationships between kin. It
would not be surprising if this combination of features were to lead to
reproductive success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blume himself inadvertently suggests this explanation when he
excludes from his analysis ‘those religious communities who do not build
and support families … (i.e. late Greek and Roman Polytheism, Gnostic
groups, the Shakers)’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;References&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day, Abby. 2011. Believing in Belonging. Oxford: Oxford University
Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; More on this in &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion-part-ii/" title="Evolution and Religion Part II"&gt;Evolution and Religion Part
II&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion-part-iii/" title="Evolution and Religion Part III"&gt;Evolution and Religion Part
III&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Abby Day"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="Michael Blume"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Ignorance and Power, Critical Studies in Education 50(3)</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/ignorance-and-power-critical-studies-in-education-503.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-31T16:15:02+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-10-31:/ignorance-and-power-critical-studies-in-education-503.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’a another exercise in the anthropology of ignorance, this time
focused on ignorance in education — a special issue of &lt;em&gt;Critical
Studies in Education&lt;/em&gt; from 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction, by Neriko Musha Doerr explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While resonating with Bourdieu’s theoretical formulation that it is
relations of dominance that create the legitimacy …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’a another exercise in the anthropology of ignorance, this time
focused on ignorance in education — a special issue of &lt;em&gt;Critical
Studies in Education&lt;/em&gt; from 2009.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction, by Neriko Musha Doerr explains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While resonating with Bourdieu’s theoretical formulation that it is
relations of dominance that create the legitimacy of knowledge, this
project pushes a step further and argues that the relations of dominance
can create legitimacy even in ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/toc/rcse20/50/3"&gt;Mini Special
Issue: Ignorance and power: acknowledgment of not knowing and relations
of dominance&lt;/a&gt; [paywall]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critical Studies in Education 50(3) (2009)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="ignorance"></category></entry><entry><title>Ignorance Mobilization – Joanne Gaudet</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/ignorance-mobilization-joanne-gaudet.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-10-31T15:17:40+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-10-31:/ignorance-mobilization-joanne-gaudet.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just come across the work of Joanne Gaudet, a PhD candidate at
the University of Ottawa who has been working on issues of ignorance and
the productivity of ignorance from a sociological — and especially
sociology of science — point of view. She has a website with a number of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just come across the work of Joanne Gaudet, a PhD candidate at
the University of Ottawa who has been working on issues of ignorance and
the productivity of ignorance from a sociological — and especially
sociology of science — point of view. She has a website with a number of
interesting looking working papers at
http://www.ignorancemobilization.com (edit: website no longer
working).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She defines ‘ignorance mobilisation’ as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ignorance Mobilization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
“The use of the borders and the limits of knowing, including the
intentional and the unintentional consideration or bracketing out of
what is not known, towards the achievement of goals (i.e., social,
cultural, political, professional, and economic)”&lt;br/&gt;
(Gaudet, 2012, Gaudet et al., 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignorance mobilization complements ‘knowledge mobilization’ in the
social scientific investigation of research and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="ignorance"></category></entry><entry><title>Cultures of Ignorance: CFP, 17th World Congress of the IUAES, Manchester 2013</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-ignorance-cfp-17th-world-congress-of-the-iuaes-manchester-2013.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-05-31T11:21:46+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-05-31:/cultures-of-ignorance-cfp-17th-world-congress-of-the-iuaes-manchester-2013.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jenny Diggins (Sussex) and I have just issued the following call for
papers for a panel on the anthropology of ignorance, to be held at the
IUAES Congress in Manchester next summer. Feel free to get in touch if
you’re considering submitting a proposal but want to discuss it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Jenny Diggins (Sussex) and I have just issued the following call for
papers for a panel on the anthropology of ignorance, to be held at the
IUAES Congress in Manchester next summer. Feel free to get in touch if
you’re considering submitting a proposal but want to discuss it
first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call for Papers at the IUAES Congress, at the University of
Manchester, 5th-10th August 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Panel Title : Cultures of Ignorance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deadline for abstracts : 13th July 2012&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is nothing new for anthropologists to be curious about things that
for us, as outsiders, are hidden from view. In Melanesia and West
Africa, where concealed ritual practices are central in customary
politics, “secrecy” has long been an ethnographic preoccupation. With
elaborate systems of esoteric knowledge, these regions have proved
particularly fertile ground for western scholars with a poetic
preference for the other-worldly. However anthropologists have rarely
paid attention to an indispensible condition of secret knowledge: the
experience of ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When faced with culturally produced forms of not-knowing, the
assumption has often been that we should set out to pierce that
ignorance. According to this logic, it is only “by peering behind the
facade that we see things as an insider rather than as outsiders and
thereby discover the truth” (Gable 1997: 215). But does uncovering
‘hidden truth’ risk distorting the way in which our interlocutors
experience (not)knowing in their daily lives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This panel invites contributions which explore the question of
ignorance from exactly the opposite direction; beginning with the
recognition that ethnographers are often far from being the only people
on the “wrong” side of this knowlege façade. The discussion will
contribute to a small but growing body of work (reviews in Mair, Kelly
&amp;amp;amp; High 2012; McGoey 2012) that aims to take ignorance seriously
– not simply as the absence of knowledge, but as an ethnographic object
in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convenors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Mair (Manchester University)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Diggins (University of Sussex)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information, or to propose a paper, please follow this
link:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.nomadit.co.uk/iuaes/iuaes2013/panels.php5?PanelID=1625"&gt;http://www.nomadit.co.uk/iuaes/iuaes2013/panels.php5?PanelID=1625&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="call for papers"></category><category term="ignorance"></category><category term="iuaes"></category><category term="jenny diggins"></category><category term="manchester"></category></entry><entry><title>The Anthropology of Ignorance</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/the-anthropology-of-ignorance.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-17T18:21:36+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-04-17:/the-anthropology-of-ignorance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012). The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/ignorance.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012).
The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High, C., Kelly, A., Mair, J. (eds.) 2012. The Anthropology of
Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach. New York &amp;amp; Basingstoke:
Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new volume on the anthropology of ignorance, which I edited with
Casey High and Ann …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012). The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/ignorance.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012).
The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High, C., Kelly, A., Mair, J. (eds.) 2012. The Anthropology of
Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach. New York &amp;amp; Basingstoke:
Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new volume on the anthropology of ignorance, which I edited with
Casey High and Ann Kelly, came out last week with Palgrave. I’m really
pleased with the finished product, and that’s all down to the
contributors who have produced some excellent chapters…and stuck to all
the deadlines—many thanks to all of you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general argument that the book advances is simply that ignorance
is something that many people value, something whose particular
characteristics in any context may have far reaching consequences, and
that it is therefore something that deserves our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropologists have been reluctant to acknowledge this in the past.
One reason for this has been because one of anthropology’s most
important roles has been to show that members of the societies in which
anthropologists typically conduct research are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; benighted
and ignorant, but actually hold quite extensive and sophisticated
knowledge about practical or technical things, such as botany, as well
as culturally important things, such as genealogies and myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we propose is a new approach—an ethnographic approach,
exemplified by the chapters in the book. Actually, we suggest this is a
new approach that is already becoming widespread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quotation from the first chapter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Making ignorance an ethnographic object is an important move because
of the questions it leads us to ask. It means asking not: There are the
things we don’t know; why is it we don’t know them? but rather, Given
that the set of things we do not know is necessarily without limit, how
and why do we become aware of particular areas of ignorance? How are
various forms of the condition of being ignorant (the equivalent of
expertise) recognized? How are forms of ignorance transmitted or taught?
How are they regulated? What kinds of roles or relationships does
ignorance depend on or produce? Do people intentionally act to develop
their awareness of ignorance? Why do people engage in the production of
forms of ignorance? What is the rationale for practices that produce
ignorance? What effects does a given form of ignorance give rise to and
how are these related to its production? How does a particular form of
ignorance affect the relationships to forms of knowledge of those in
whom it is produced?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table of contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making Ignorance an Ethnographic Object —&lt;/em&gt; Jonathan Mair,
Ann Kelly, and Casey High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sarax and the City: Almsgiving and Anonymous Objects in Dakar,
Senegal —&lt;/em&gt; Gretchen Pfeil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discourses of the Coming: Ignorance, Forgetting, and Prolepsis
in Japanese Life-Historiography —&lt;/em&gt; Shunsuke Nozawa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evoking Ignorance: Abstraction and Anonymity in Social
Networking’s Ideals of Reciprocity —&lt;/em&gt; David S. Leitner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Between Knowing and Being: Ignorance in Anthropology and
Amazonian&lt;/em&gt; Shamanism — Casey High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I Don’t Know Why He Did It. It Happened by Itself”: Causality
and Suicide in Northwest Greenland&lt;/em&gt; — Janne Flora&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inhabiting the Temporary: Patience and Uncertainty among Urban
Squatters in Buenos Aires —&lt;/em&gt; Valeria Procupez&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Fertility. Freedom. Finally.”: Cultivating Hope in the Face of
Uncertain Futures among Egg-Freezing Women —&lt;/em&gt; Tiffany Romain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="almsgiving"></category><category term="amazon"></category><category term="‘ann kelly’"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="argentina"></category><category term="biography"></category><category term="book"></category><category term="‘casey high’"></category><category term="fertility"></category><category term="greenland"></category><category term="housing"></category><category term="ignorance"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="networking"></category><category term="NRT"></category><category term="senegal"></category><category term="shamanism"></category><category term="suicide"></category><category term="‘the gift’"></category></entry></feed>