<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - argentina</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/argentina.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>The Anthropology of Ignorance</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/the-anthropology-of-ignorance.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-17T18:21:36+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-04-17:/the-anthropology-of-ignorance.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012). The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/ignorance.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012).
The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High, C., Kelly, A., Mair, J. (eds.) 2012. The Anthropology of
Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach. New York &amp;amp; Basingstoke:
Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new volume on the anthropology of ignorance, which I edited with
Casey High and Ann …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012). The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/ignorance.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;High, C., A. Kelly &amp;amp; J. Mair (2012).
The Anthropology of Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High, C., Kelly, A., Mair, J. (eds.) 2012. The Anthropology of
Ignorance: An Ethnographic Approach. New York &amp;amp; Basingstoke:
Palgrave Macmillan.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new volume on the anthropology of ignorance, which I edited with
Casey High and Ann Kelly, came out last week with Palgrave. I’m really
pleased with the finished product, and that’s all down to the
contributors who have produced some excellent chapters…and stuck to all
the deadlines—many thanks to all of you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general argument that the book advances is simply that ignorance
is something that many people value, something whose particular
characteristics in any context may have far reaching consequences, and
that it is therefore something that deserves our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anthropologists have been reluctant to acknowledge this in the past.
One reason for this has been because one of anthropology’s most
important roles has been to show that members of the societies in which
anthropologists typically conduct research are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; benighted
and ignorant, but actually hold quite extensive and sophisticated
knowledge about practical or technical things, such as botany, as well
as culturally important things, such as genealogies and myth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we propose is a new approach—an ethnographic approach,
exemplified by the chapters in the book. Actually, we suggest this is a
new approach that is already becoming widespread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quotation from the first chapter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Making ignorance an ethnographic object is an important move because
of the questions it leads us to ask. It means asking not: There are the
things we don’t know; why is it we don’t know them? but rather, Given
that the set of things we do not know is necessarily without limit, how
and why do we become aware of particular areas of ignorance? How are
various forms of the condition of being ignorant (the equivalent of
expertise) recognized? How are forms of ignorance transmitted or taught?
How are they regulated? What kinds of roles or relationships does
ignorance depend on or produce? Do people intentionally act to develop
their awareness of ignorance? Why do people engage in the production of
forms of ignorance? What is the rationale for practices that produce
ignorance? What effects does a given form of ignorance give rise to and
how are these related to its production? How does a particular form of
ignorance affect the relationships to forms of knowledge of those in
whom it is produced?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The table of contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Making Ignorance an Ethnographic Object —&lt;/em&gt; Jonathan Mair,
Ann Kelly, and Casey High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sarax and the City: Almsgiving and Anonymous Objects in Dakar,
Senegal —&lt;/em&gt; Gretchen Pfeil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Discourses of the Coming: Ignorance, Forgetting, and Prolepsis
in Japanese Life-Historiography —&lt;/em&gt; Shunsuke Nozawa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evoking Ignorance: Abstraction and Anonymity in Social
Networking’s Ideals of Reciprocity —&lt;/em&gt; David S. Leitner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Between Knowing and Being: Ignorance in Anthropology and
Amazonian&lt;/em&gt; Shamanism — Casey High&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I Don’t Know Why He Did It. It Happened by Itself”: Causality
and Suicide in Northwest Greenland&lt;/em&gt; — Janne Flora&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Inhabiting the Temporary: Patience and Uncertainty among Urban
Squatters in Buenos Aires —&lt;/em&gt; Valeria Procupez&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Fertility. Freedom. Finally.”: Cultivating Hope in the Face of
Uncertain Futures among Egg-Freezing Women —&lt;/em&gt; Tiffany Romain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="almsgiving"></category><category term="amazon"></category><category term="‘ann kelly’"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="argentina"></category><category term="biography"></category><category term="book"></category><category term="‘casey high’"></category><category term="fertility"></category><category term="greenland"></category><category term="housing"></category><category term="ignorance"></category><category term="japan"></category><category term="networking"></category><category term="NRT"></category><category term="senegal"></category><category term="shamanism"></category><category term="suicide"></category><category term="‘the gift’"></category></entry></feed>