<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - business</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/business.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2023-06-15T16:26:59+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Oscar Krüger article: What’s in a container?</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2023/06/oscar-kruger-article-whats-in-a-container/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-06-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-15T16:26:59+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2023-06-01:/2023/06/oscar-kruger-article-whats-in-a-container/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are all consumers of many kinds of goods, and in that capacity, we
can hardly be unaware of the importance of the containers in which those
goods are packaged. Containers protect and condition what they contain,
and they can be part of the experience of consumption, enhancing or
limiting …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are all consumers of many kinds of goods, and in that capacity, we
can hardly be unaware of the importance of the containers in which those
goods are packaged. Containers protect and condition what they contain,
and they can be part of the experience of consumption, enhancing or
limiting our enjoyment of the&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are less accustomed to thinking about the role of containers in
the process of production. I read a fascinating ethnographic article
recently that draws attention to just&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oscar Krüger, a social anthropologist at Lund University, spent
several years researching small wine production in Italy (I was
fortunate to be able to contribute to the supervision of his PhD on the
topic). In ‘Peasant in a Bottle: Infrastructures of Containment for an
Italian Wine Cooperative’, published in &lt;em&gt;Ethnos&lt;/em&gt;, he explains the
importance of different kinds of containers of wine for artisinal&amp;nbsp;producers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard designs of the glass wine bottle were established long
ago. There are only a few options, and any elaboration is taken to be
flashy, rather than as a sign of quality. But that doesn’t mean that the
bottle is unimportant for the&amp;nbsp;producer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the wine producers’ point of view, there are two ways of selling
wine into the consumer market, distinguished by the type of container
used. Most wine is sold to wholesalers in tanks, to be blended and
bottled later on, close to the end market. Bottling at the site of
production is more expensive, but is a seal of quality. That is because
it allows what is distinctive about the product–above all its expression
of a specific &lt;em&gt;terroir&lt;/em&gt;–to be preserved from the vinyard to the
table. As Oscar writes, ‘by integrating the act of sealing into the
grape-growing farm itself, the winemakers ensure that they themselves
are made present at that final point, irrespective of whether it is
Turin or Tokyo’ (p.9). The bottle remains sealed until it is opened by
the consumer, whereas wine sold in tanks will be decanted into a series
of different containers before it is bottled, breaking the connection
with the specific site of&amp;nbsp;production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This connection between the glass bottle and the marketable quality
of the character of the wine of a single estate goes back to the 1660s,
where the idea of &lt;em&gt;terroir&lt;/em&gt; as the expression of the unchanging
and unique ‘taste of the place’ developed early. The extension of this
idea in Italy, as &lt;em&gt;territorialitá&lt;/em&gt;, has been seen as a way to
escape the downward pressure on prices that has come with the
development of commodity markets in food and drinks. Tying a specific
product–first wine, then a host of other comestible products–to a
specific place allows both product and place to acquire greater
distinctiveness and greater value. Clearly where this connection is
facilitated by the relatively small and heavy glass bottle, it comes at
a cost for the producer, and for the&amp;nbsp;environment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="business"></category><category term="consumption"></category><category term="production"></category><category term="wine"></category><category term="ethnography"></category></entry></feed>