<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - ethnography of belief</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/ethnography-of-belief.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Needham’s review of Paul Veyne’s ‘Did the Greeks believe in their myths?’</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-17T13:45:57+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-08-17:/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my thoughts in my &lt;a href="../2015-08-17-rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-belief/"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to Needham’s review of Veyne’s book. The review is short, and
much is taken up with flattering comments on Veyne’s style, but overall
the conclusion is negative—he characterises the argument as ‘erratic and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This post is a continuation of my thoughts in my &lt;a href="../2015-08-17-rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-belief/"&gt;previous
post&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to Needham’s review of Veyne’s book. The review is short, and
much is taken up with flattering comments on Veyne’s style, but overall
the conclusion is negative—he characterises the argument as ‘erratic and
inconsistent’. On my reading, Needham makes three substantive points,
which I shall deal with one by one here in order of importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The only criticism that really has bite is that Veyne is vague about
what the key terms in his analysis—belief and truth—mean to him. Partly
on the basis of Veyne’s previous work, Needham reads &lt;em&gt;Did the
Greeks…?&lt;/em&gt; as an exercise in epistemological relativism, and makes a
version of the usual objection to the paradoxes of relativism: if truth
is always to be defined in local terms, in relation to historically
specific programmes of truth, as Veyne would have it, then what exactly
does Veyne mean when he says, absolutely, and not qualified by any
context, that truth is plural?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, Veyne actually concentrates not on belief but on
truth, but only to place himself in a further difficulty. He concedes
that ‘truth’ too means so many things, yet he passes over the variety of
theories of truth and, in the end, commits himself consistently to none.
The nearest he gets to a steady acceptance is to say that truths and
interests, which are both limited and arbitrary, are ‘two different
terms for the same thing’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham is right to call Veyne out for not clarifying his terms, and
attributing this weakness to strong epistemological relativism is not an
unreasonable interpretation. However, I believe another reading is
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne details the variety of ‘regimes of belief’ in terms of
different truth conditions and specific practices, such as the use of
footnotes in academic writing, with which they are associated. These
things are the specific form that believing has, historically taken. But
it is still possible to speak of believing in the abstract, as the
category to which all these concrete modes of belief belong. What is it
that makes the ordinary ancient Greek’s vague and lethargic belief in
gods and heroes an instance of the same class of phenomenon as the
mediaeval lawyer’s insistence on footnotes, and the modern newspaper
reader’s suspicion of bias? They are all specifications of the practical
and social relationship between thinker and what the thinker accepts as
truth. To put it more pithily, belief is about a relationship to a body
of truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit, it’s not clear from Veyne’s text that this is what
&lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; means by belief and truth, but it’s a reading that makes
sense of his concrete claims, and saves his general conclusions from
Needham’s anti-relativist criticism. Needham is right that Veyne is
unclear on this score, and clarifying the meaning of the general
category of belief, and of the general category of truth on which it
depends will be an important task for any ethnographic approach to
belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="2" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He complains that Veyne, in seeking to understand belief, did not
take into account the attempts of philosophers such as Wittgenstein,
Hume, Kant, and so on to do the same thing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These writers were engaged in what Veyne describes as an exercise of
‘the constitutive imagination’. Like the ancient and modern historians
whom Veyne describes, they were engaged in shaping programmes of truth,
legitimising some ‘regimes of belief’ and delegitimising others. They
were not in the business of describing the plural programmes of truth of
others, and they would only have had a place in the book alongside the
mediaeval jurists and modern journalists that Veyne—as case studies of
the kind of second-order belief theory and practice that Veyne is
interested in describing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, Veyne is writing at a higher level of generalisation
or abstraction than Kant et al., and for a different purpose. The
philosophers’ question would not have been ‘Did the Greeks believe in
their myths’, but the logically posterior question, ‘Were the Greeks
right to (dis)believe in their myths?’, which is only meaningful once it
is established whether or not (or to what extent, in what senses) they
did, in fact, believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="3" type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, Needham chides Veyne for not taking account of ‘sceptical
anthropology’. He argues that ethnographers have succeeded in explaining
the kinds god-language that Veyne’s question raises, but without
resorting to the notion of belief. He concludes that these writers,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;confirm that it is not ‘pointless’, as Veyne proposes, to try to
determine the true thought of other peoples, but that we shall not do so
if we attribute our thoughts to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No page references are given in the review, but thanks to Google, it
is possible to trace the passage in Veyne’s book to which Needham
refers. Needham suggests that Veyne says it’s pointless ‘…to determine
the true thought of other peoples thought’. The ‘pointless’ here is
taken out of context and is quite misleading. In fact, Veyne was not
saying it was hopeless to try to understand ‘other people’s’ thought,
but that when faced with contradictory forms of thought, one must
recognise the plurality rather than trying to explain it away. The full
passage reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Struggling to determine ‘the’ true thought of these people is
pointless, and it is equally unproductive to attempt to resolve these
contradictory thoughts by attributing one to popular religion and the
other to the beliefs of the privileged social classes. (Veyne
1988:89)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sceptical approach that Needham recommends begins by setting
aside the question of belief. It may have found other explanations for
religious language, and they may be illuminating, but this approach
cannot even recognise the plurality of modes of belief that Veyne draws
our attention to and makes it his business to describe and
understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, then, Needham’s critical review does not persuade me that
Veyne’s way of understanding belief is not a really critical piece in
understanding human thought, though Needham is right to say that Veyne
is vague about his key terms. They’re still arguing in my head and Veyne
is still winning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Needham, Rodney. ‘Reviewed Work: Did the Greeks Believe in Their
Myths? An Essay on the Constitutive Imagination. by Paul Veyne, transl.
Paula Wissing’. Man (New Series), Vol. 25, No. 1 (Mar., 1990),
pp. 157-158.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Veyne, Paul. &lt;em&gt;Did the Greeks believe in their myths?: An essay on
the constitutive imagination&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
1988.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="belief scepticism"></category><category term="ethnography of belief"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="Rodney Needham"></category></entry><entry><title>Rodney Needham and Paul Veyne on religious belief</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-religious-belief.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-17T13:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-08-17:/rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-religious-belief.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804131"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by Rodney Needham
of Paul Veyne’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the Greeks
believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I was quite intrigued by this as these
two authors are representatives of two approaches to the study of
religious belief and the anthropology of belief I have been thinking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804131"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by Rodney Needham
of Paul Veyne’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the Greeks
believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I was quite intrigued by this as these
two authors are representatives of two approaches to the study of
religious belief and the anthropology of belief I have been thinking
about &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory/"&gt;for
a while&lt;/a&gt; . They have often squabbled in my head, and in my
imagination, Veyne always wins the argument, so I was curious to see
what Needham would make of Veyne’s argument and the strong implicit
critique of his own position it entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social scientists have a difficult relationship with religious
belief. On the one hand, belief is often absolutely central to accounts
of religious communities and practice: Group A carries out this practice
because of a belief X, religious innovator B used to do Y, so we can
conclude he believed Z, and so on. Such accounts are ubiquitous, in the
everyday language of religious people and non-specialists, &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;psychologists of
religion&lt;/a&gt;, and almost just as much, for all their denials, in the
language of social scientists. Because this model of religious life sees
belief-language as being a more or less reliable reflection of religious
people’s understanding of the world, it is known (mainly by its critics)
as ‘intellectualism’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, academic students of religion have long argued
that belief is just not what most religious traditions are about, and
that the use of the concept of belief is deeply misleading. I call this
position ‘belief scepticism’. Academic belief scepticism goes back at
least as far as William Robertson Smith’s 1889 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=oAfiFpR7sv8C"&gt;Lectures on the
Religion of the Semites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. There are many variations, but a
general outline of this position is as follows: we modern students of
religion think that religion is all about a set of propositions that
followers believe to be true, but this view of belief as propositional
and central to religious life is a relatively modern Christian
innovation; other religious traditions are more about practice or
symbolic expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This belief scepticism argument has also been extended to
Christianity, for example, by Abby Day, who recently &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review/"&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt;
that religion in the UK, including the that of her Christian
interviewees (not all were Christian), was about social belonging and
morality and not about propositional belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both intellectualism and belief scepticism have important
things to teach us about religious and other belief, I do not accept
either (1) that religious belief language is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; a
straightforward representation of systematically related propositions to
which followers assent, as the intellectualists are alleged to claim, or
(2) that belief-language &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; has another function (part of
practice, deference to a social system, expression of moral values) and
&lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; refers to propositional beliefs, except perhaps in the
case of (some) Christians, as the belief sceptics often argue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have long been a proponent of a &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory/"&gt;third
position&lt;/a&gt;, which I call the ‘ethnographic’ approach to belief—it
might equally be described as ‘historical’. This simply means
recognising that it is not only first order information—’God is three
persons in one substance’, ‘twins are birds’, ‘actions have
consequences’—that varies between persons, cultures, periods of history,
but also the second-order, meta-cognitive information and practices
relating to how one is supposed to relate cognitively and otherwise to
this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anthropologist and philosopher Rodney Needham wrote a long and
influential book making the belief-sceptic case, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=khWLQgAACAAJ"&gt;Belief, language
and experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1972). I have always found his arguments in the
book problematic and I’m always surprised by the deference with which
his argument is treated by contemporary anthropologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Veyne is a French historian of classical antiquity, who was
closely associated with Foucault. His 1983 book &lt;em&gt;Les Grecs ont-ils
cru à leurs mythes?&lt;/em&gt;, published in English translation in 1988 as
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the
Greeks believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is, I think, an exemplary
instance of an ethnographic approach to belief that takes into account
different styles, or ‘modes’ of belief, as much as the content to which
belief was applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His answer to the eponymous question is ‘yes and no’—the ordinary
Greek did not believe in myth in the same way that he believed in things
he had experienced directly, but he still believed that the events
recounted in myths were true. The different modes of truth were
distinguished by different truth conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne neatly demonstrates the importance of understanding the
plurality of modes of belief or ‘programmes of truth’ by contrasting the
attitudes of the Greek in the street with those of classical historians
such as Pausanias and Thucydides. The historians no less than hoi polloi
believe the events described by myths were true, but their activity was
motivated by a second-order imperative that insisted that there could
only be one programme of truth. The aim of their practice was to apply
reason, &lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt;, in order to reconcile the apparent
contradictions between &lt;em&gt;mythos—&lt;/em&gt;myths about gods and heroes—and
stories of the contemporary lives of ordinary people&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day, Abby. &lt;em&gt;Believing in belonging: Belief and social identity in
the modern world&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham, Rodney. &lt;em&gt;Belief, language, and experience&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford:
Blackwell, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="rw mbs"&gt;
Needham, Rodney. ‘Reviewed Work: &lt;cite&gt;Did the Greeks Believe in Their
Myths? An Essay on the Constitutive Imagination.&lt;/cite&gt; by Paul Veyne,
transl. Paula Wissing’. &lt;cite&gt;Man &lt;/cite&gt;(New Series), Vol. 25, No. 1
(Mar., 1990), pp. 157-158.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, William Robertson. &lt;em&gt;Lectures on the Religion of the
Semites: First series. The fundamental institutions&lt;/em&gt;. Appleton,
1889.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne, Paul. &lt;em&gt;Did the Greeks believe in their myths?: An essay on
the constitutive imagination&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
1988.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology of belief"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="belief scepticism"></category><category term="ethnography of belief"></category><category term="Greek myth"></category><category term="intellectualism"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="programmes of truth"></category><category term="regimes of belief"></category><category term="Rodney Needham"></category><category term="truth"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry></feed>