<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - ghosts</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/ghosts.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Abby Day’s Believing in Belonging: Review</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-06-30T15:16:07+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-06-30:/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s my review of Abby Day’s Believing in Belonging which appeared
in last year’s edition of the &lt;a href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/arrs/2012/00000003/00000001/art00019"&gt;Journal
of Religion and Society&lt;/a&gt;. Though I didn’t quite buy the theoretical
argument of the book, I thought the substantive work on people’s
attitudes towards institutionalised religion, gods …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s my review of Abby Day’s Believing in Belonging which appeared
in last year’s edition of the &lt;a href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/arrs/2012/00000003/00000001/art00019"&gt;Journal
of Religion and Society&lt;/a&gt;. Though I didn’t quite buy the theoretical
argument of the book, I thought the substantive work on people’s
attitudes towards institutionalised religion, gods, ghosts and fate was
fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commentary on the census is also very useful. I referred to that
aspect of the work in a &lt;a href="../2012-11-16-evolution-and-religion"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, where I
questioned an evolutionary explanation of religion that relied on data
from historical censuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="review-of-believing-in-belonging-by-abby-day"&gt;Review of
&lt;em&gt;Believing in Belonging&lt;/em&gt; by Abby Day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/berghahn/arrs;jsessionid=1gxhglhhneg0a.victoria" title="Religion and Society: Advances in Research"&gt;Religion and Society:
Advances in Research&lt;/a&gt;, Volume 3, Number 1, 2012 , pp. 211-241(31)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Believing in Belonging&lt;/em&gt; is a study based mainly on a series
of interviews conducted in the early 2000s in the north of England.
Suspecting that sociological studies of religious affiliation were
failing to capture something important, Day asked her interviewees
instead about ‘belief’. In the substantive chapters she outlines the
main issues that emerged from these conversations: community and
identity, relations with kin, enduring relations with the dead, the
operation of fate or providence, and the importance of morality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most interesting finding relates to a puzzle about contemporary
religious belief. In the 2001 census, which was the first to include a
question on religious identity, 72% of respondents identified themselves
as Christian. This was interpreted jubilantly by many, Day notes, as a
refutation of the secularization thesis. The census was not the first
survey to show that a high proportion of British people continue to
identify themselves as Christian, but it added to a longstanding
sociological puzzle: while a high proportion of people in postwar Europe
are still willing to call themselves Christian, other markers of
religion, such as participation in acts of worship, show a dramatic and
continuing decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two established explanations for this discrepancy. One is
that many of the self-identified Christians are ‘nominal’ Christians,
who identify themselves as Christian if asked, and may attend church for
weddings and funerals, but otherwise do not think twice about belief. On
this interpretation, the high rates of religious identification in
surveys such as the census tell us little or nothing about the decline
of belief in religion. The other explanation, most influentially
advanced by Grace Davie, is that the phenomenon is just another aspect
of the individualization of western societies, in which traditional
communal institutions have lost their authority and people engage with
culture on their own terms. On this view, the fall in church attendance
cannot be taken as evidence of a corresponding loss of belief, rather,
people continue ‘believing without belonging’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day’s research supports neither explanation. She finds that her
interviewees can be divided into ‘theocentrics’, who see a relationship
with God at the center of everything they do, and ‘anthropocentrics’,
who do not. Theocentrics tend to be quite hostile in their evaluation of
anthropocentrics, and vice versa. But the surprising and significant
finding is that the boundaries of these groups do not coincide with the
boundary between those who identify themselves as belonging to a
religion and those who do not. About half of the interviewees who
identified themselves as Christian were ‘anthropocentric’, and many of
those were assertively atheist as well as rejecting the authority of
institutional religion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a problem for the ‘believing without belonging’ school,
because it suggests that little can be assumed about people’s acceptance
of religious beliefs on the basis of their self-declared religious
identity. On the other hand, many ‘anthropocentric’ respondents, whether
or not they felt they belonged to a particular religion, did believe
they had experienced ghosts, and that the hand of fate acted in their
lives. This means that neither falling church attendances or even
outright antipathy to religion can be taken as clear evidence of
rationalization of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day’s own interpretation of her findings is that claiming, or
‘performing’, religious identity through surveys and narratives is a way
of asserting a sort of ascribed cultural heritage, and simultaneously
excluding ethnic others from it. Beliefs about other things—values, the
dead, and so on—are used in the same way to express the importance of
various social relationships, and often to exclude weak groups including
women and children. Day’s ‘neo-Durkheimian’ conclusion is that belief is
ultimately a matter of ‘the social’: ‘believing in belonging’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the detail of Day’s interviews is of interest. For example,
the way in which informants sometimes reveal their own awareness of
having decided to believe that they can speak to their kin beyond the
grave, because the alternative would be unbearable, or the fact that
ghosts are experienced in an embodied, sensually rich way, but rarely
visually, or that among her respondents, only deceased kin were
experienced in this way, not friends or unrelated strangers.
Interviewees say they believe morality is doing to others as one would
be done by, but in practice, they mean ‘doing to’ people like
themselves, and various ethnic, or gendered ‘others’ turn out not to
merit the same treatment. Many ‘anthropocentric’ people say that being
culturally Christian means that their values are based on the Ten
Commandments, and do not notice that they have tacitly edited out
Commandments I – IV, which stipulate proper behavior in relation to
God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This material alone makes the book a valuable contribution to the
literature. However, in terms of its theoretical aims—to provide a sound
basis for understanding belief—the book is less successful. Day is
ambitious in this respect and there are theoretical claims throughout.
Here space allows me to mention only the most important of them, Day’s
argument (drawing on Austin and Butler) that belief should be understood
as ‘performative’ in the sense that the narration of beliefs brings
about concrete effects. However, the claim is nowhere clearly explained,
and Day’s usage is slippery: sometimes the effect of performance is the
creation of a community of identity or some other object of belief,
sometimes it is the creation of the belief itself, sometimes she seems
to be claiming that the performance &lt;em&gt;itself&lt;/em&gt; is the belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason that defining ‘belief’ is so important to Day’s
argument—and this is also the reason it is so difficult to define—is
that she seeks to displace the concept of ‘religion’ from its central
position in social scientific work, but seems to want to replace it with
an equivalent concept that covers much the same ground, including fate,
morality and communication with the dead. But there is no reason to
think that the different things the interviewees speak about under the
rubric of ‘belief’ cover, from their point of view, a single field of
thought or activity, and therefore no reason to expect to be able to
find a unifying definition, or even that a family resemblance
relationship obtains between them. Day sets out to replace the survey
designers’ blunt questions about religious affiliation, which assume too
much, with a more inductive approach, but the design of her structured
interviews, starting with the question, ‘What do you believe in?’
incorporates its own assumptions, above all that there is a single,
coherent phenomenon that corresponds to ‘believing in’. Day’s
descriptions of the anxiety evoked in her participants by her first
question—for instance, ‘Sometimes informants demonstrated surprise at
the question and needed a few seconds to gather his or her [sic]
thoughts. Some physically drew back and looked at me in shock…’
(p. 41)—suggest that for them ‘believing in’ corresponded to no clearly
defined or salient category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day has not solved the problem of belief, but notwithstanding these
limitations, her book is an important contribution to the literature
that has significant implications for future empirical and theoretical
work, as well as for public policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Abby Day"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="census"></category><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="fate"></category><category term="ghosts"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="uk"></category></entry></feed>