<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - Greek myth</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/greek-myth.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T02:27:48+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Rodney Needham and Paul Veyne on religious belief</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-religious-belief.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-08-17T13:30:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T02:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-08-17:/rodney-needham-and-paul-veyne-on-religious-belief.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804131"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by Rodney Needham
of Paul Veyne’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the Greeks
believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I was quite intrigued by this as these
two authors are representatives of two approaches to the study of
religious belief and the anthropology of belief I have been thinking …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a &lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2804131"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; by Rodney Needham
of Paul Veyne’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the Greeks
believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I was quite intrigued by this as these
two authors are representatives of two approaches to the study of
religious belief and the anthropology of belief I have been thinking
about &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory/"&gt;for
a while&lt;/a&gt; . They have often squabbled in my head, and in my
imagination, Veyne always wins the argument, so I was curious to see
what Needham would make of Veyne’s argument and the strong implicit
critique of his own position it entails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social scientists have a difficult relationship with religious
belief. On the one hand, belief is often absolutely central to accounts
of religious communities and practice: Group A carries out this practice
because of a belief X, religious innovator B used to do Y, so we can
conclude he believed Z, and so on. Such accounts are ubiquitous, in the
everyday language of religious people and non-specialists, &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;psychologists of
religion&lt;/a&gt;, and almost just as much, for all their denials, in the
language of social scientists. Because this model of religious life sees
belief-language as being a more or less reliable reflection of religious
people’s understanding of the world, it is known (mainly by its critics)
as ‘intellectualism’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, academic students of religion have long argued
that belief is just not what most religious traditions are about, and
that the use of the concept of belief is deeply misleading. I call this
position ‘belief scepticism’. Academic belief scepticism goes back at
least as far as William Robertson Smith’s 1889 &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=oAfiFpR7sv8C"&gt;Lectures on the
Religion of the Semites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. There are many variations, but a
general outline of this position is as follows: we modern students of
religion think that religion is all about a set of propositions that
followers believe to be true, but this view of belief as propositional
and central to religious life is a relatively modern Christian
innovation; other religious traditions are more about practice or
symbolic expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This belief scepticism argument has also been extended to
Christianity, for example, by Abby Day, who recently &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/abby-days-believing-in-belonging-review/"&gt;argued&lt;/a&gt;
that religion in the UK, including the that of her Christian
interviewees (not all were Christian), was about social belonging and
morality and not about propositional belief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although both intellectualism and belief scepticism have important
things to teach us about religious and other belief, I do not accept
either (1) that religious belief language is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; a
straightforward representation of systematically related propositions to
which followers assent, as the intellectualists are alleged to claim, or
(2) that belief-language &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; has another function (part of
practice, deference to a social system, expression of moral values) and
&lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; refers to propositional beliefs, except perhaps in the
case of (some) Christians, as the belief sceptics often argue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have long been a proponent of a &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory/"&gt;third
position&lt;/a&gt;, which I call the ‘ethnographic’ approach to belief—it
might equally be described as ‘historical’. This simply means
recognising that it is not only first order information—’God is three
persons in one substance’, ‘twins are birds’, ‘actions have
consequences’—that varies between persons, cultures, periods of history,
but also the second-order, meta-cognitive information and practices
relating to how one is supposed to relate cognitively and otherwise to
this information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anthropologist and philosopher Rodney Needham wrote a long and
influential book making the belief-sceptic case, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=khWLQgAACAAJ"&gt;Belief, language
and experience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1972). I have always found his arguments in the
book problematic and I’m always surprised by the deference with which
his argument is treated by contemporary anthropologists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Veyne is a French historian of classical antiquity, who was
closely associated with Foucault. His 1983 book &lt;em&gt;Les Grecs ont-ils
cru à leurs mythes?&lt;/em&gt;, published in English translation in 1988 as
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=EpbZLRPGgBsC"&gt;Did the
Greeks believe in their myths?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is, I think, an exemplary
instance of an ethnographic approach to belief that takes into account
different styles, or ‘modes’ of belief, as much as the content to which
belief was applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;His answer to the eponymous question is ‘yes and no’—the ordinary
Greek did not believe in myth in the same way that he believed in things
he had experienced directly, but he still believed that the events
recounted in myths were true. The different modes of truth were
distinguished by different truth conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne neatly demonstrates the importance of understanding the
plurality of modes of belief or ‘programmes of truth’ by contrasting the
attitudes of the Greek in the street with those of classical historians
such as Pausanias and Thucydides. The historians no less than hoi polloi
believe the events described by myths were true, but their activity was
motivated by a second-order imperative that insisted that there could
only be one programme of truth. The aim of their practice was to apply
reason, &lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt;, in order to reconcile the apparent
contradictions between &lt;em&gt;mythos—&lt;/em&gt;myths about gods and heroes—and
stories of the contemporary lives of ordinary people&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/needhams-review-of-paul-veynes-did-the-greeks-believe-in-their-myths/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Day, Abby. &lt;em&gt;Believing in belonging: Belief and social identity in
the modern world&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needham, Rodney. &lt;em&gt;Belief, language, and experience&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford:
Blackwell, 1972.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="rw mbs"&gt;
Needham, Rodney. ‘Reviewed Work: &lt;cite&gt;Did the Greeks Believe in Their
Myths? An Essay on the Constitutive Imagination.&lt;/cite&gt; by Paul Veyne,
transl. Paula Wissing’. &lt;cite&gt;Man &lt;/cite&gt;(New Series), Vol. 25, No. 1
(Mar., 1990), pp. 157-158.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smith, William Robertson. &lt;em&gt;Lectures on the Religion of the
Semites: First series. The fundamental institutions&lt;/em&gt;. Appleton,
1889.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veyne, Paul. &lt;em&gt;Did the Greeks believe in their myths?: An essay on
the constitutive imagination&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press,
1988.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology of belief"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="belief scepticism"></category><category term="ethnography of belief"></category><category term="Greek myth"></category><category term="intellectualism"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="programmes of truth"></category><category term="regimes of belief"></category><category term="Rodney Needham"></category><category term="truth"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry></feed>