<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - inter-disciplinarity</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/inter-disciplinarity.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T09:54:37+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>CRASSH Project: Speaking Ethically Across Borders</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/crassh-project-speaking-ethically-across-borders.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T09:54:37+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-07:/crassh-project-speaking-ethically-across-borders.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am currently a research fellow at &lt;a href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;CRASSH&lt;/a&gt;, the Centre for Research
in the Arts, Social Sciences and Humanities, at &lt;a href="http://www.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;Cambridge University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’m working on is an interdisciplinary project on
‘Speaking Ethically Across Borders’. Right now I’m planning a reading
group on the topic …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am currently a research fellow at &lt;a href="http://www.crassh.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;CRASSH&lt;/a&gt;, the Centre for Research
in the Arts, Social Sciences and Humanities, at &lt;a href="http://www.cam.ac.uk/"&gt;Cambridge University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’m working on is an interdisciplinary project on
‘Speaking Ethically Across Borders’. Right now I’m planning a reading
group on the topic for next term. The outline is below, together with
some sample readings. If anyone has any suggestions for good readings on
this theme, from any discipline, please let me know by email or in the
comments below. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, this is related to my last post: the conversations I am
interested in for this project could be seen as self-conscious attempts
to overcome potential conversations at cross-purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="speaking-ethically-across-borders"&gt;Speaking ethically across
borders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A conversation between Western Christendom and the Mongol Empire: Pope Innocent IV sends a mission to Central Asia, carrying one of a series of letters that were exchanged between the pontiffs and the Mongol khans in the thirteenth century. (Source: Wikipedia)" src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/AscelinOfCremone.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;A conversation between Western
Christendom and the Mongol Empire:&lt;br/&gt;
Pope Innocent IV sends a mission to Central Asia, carrying one of a
series of letters that were exchanged between the pontiffs and the
Mongol khans in the thirteenth century. (Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychologists such as Judith Smetana have argued that the distinction
between moral rule and social convention is innate and universal. That
may be so, but knowing that there is a difference is not the same as
knowing where the line can be drawn that divides the two. When we are in
familiar settings, the differences between tradition, habit, and
pragmatic efficiency on the one hand, and ethical considerations about
value and duty are frequently elided: there are a limited number of
given, concrete ways of living life, and most of our choices will be
made from among them. Even innovations justified on moral grounds will
silently incorporate much that is conventional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when people speak ethically across regional boundaries, they must
face the problem of finding ways to render the ethics of different
regions commensurate, either by translating local, thick ethical
practices of one or both sides into the thin common currency of some
universalist morality, or by claiming that, in so far as the essentials
are concerned, what appear to be quite different values or practices are
in fact compatible. In either case, there is a need to agree on a place
to draw the line dividing universal or shared essence from contingent
cultural convention, to decide whether it is the specific practices that
are valued, or only the underlying principle, only their effects, or
some combination of these. This makes these conversations an ideal site
for scholars interested in understanding moral reasoning and its
relation to practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="possible-examples-of-conversations-across-borders"&gt;Possible
examples of conversations across borders&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="A Jesuit in Confucian ceremonial robes during the period of the Confucian Rites Controversy - rival claims to moral authority between rival regional powers with cosmopolitan aspirations. Source: Wikipedia." src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/NicolasTrigaultInChineseCostume.jpg"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;A Jesuit in Confucian ceremonial robes
during the period of the Confucian Rites Controversy - rival claims to
moral authority between rival regional powers with cosmopolitan
aspirations. Source: Wikipedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the universalization of local ethical traditions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conversely, the vernacularization of cosmopolitan ethics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;civilizing and proselytizing missions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempts of diaspora populations to adapt the ethical culture of the
contemporary, historical, or imagined home region to life in a variety
of different moral environments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attempts to preserve a regional moral order in the face of
modernization by separating &lt;em&gt;ethos&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;techne&lt;/em&gt; (many
fascinating examples to draw here from East Asia, including the May
Fourth Movement and Deng Xiao Ping’s ‘Socialism with Chinese
Characteristics’)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="sample-bibliography"&gt;Sample Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bakken, Borge. 2000. The Exemplary Society: Human Improvement, Social
Control, and the Dangers of Modernity in China. Oxford: Oxford
University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buckser, A. 2008. “Cultural Change and the Meanings of Belief in
Jewish Copenhagen.” Social Analysis 52 (1): 39–55.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humphrey, C. 2007. “Alternative Freedoms.” Proceedings of the
American Philosophical Society 151 (1): 1–10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laidlaw, James. 2010. Ethical Traditions in Question: Diaspora
Jainism and the Environmental and Animal Liberation Movements. In
Ethical Life in South Asia. Edited by Anand Pandian and Daud Ali.
Bloomington: Indiana University Press: 61-80&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nussbaum, Martha. 2011. “Patriotism and Cosmopolitanism.” In &lt;em&gt;The
Cosmopolitanism Reader&lt;/em&gt;, ed. David Held and Garrett Wallace Brown,
155-178. Cambridge: Polity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roy, Olivier. 2006. “Islam in the West or Western Islam? The
Disconnect of Religion and Culture.” Hedgehog Review 8 (1/2): 127.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rapport, N. (1998) The potential of human rights in a post-cultural
world. Social Anthropology. 6/3: 381-388.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sheldon Pollock. 1998. “The Cosmopolitan Vernacular.” The Journal of
Asian Studies 57 (1): 6-37.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schmieder, F. 2000. “Cum Hora Undecima: The Incorporation of Asia
into the Orbis Christianus.” In Christianizing Peoples and Converting
Individuals, ed. Guyda Armstrong and Ian N. Wood, 259–65. Turnhout:
Brepols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turner, B.S. 2002. “Cosmopolitan Virtue, Globalization and
Patriotism.” Theory, Culture &amp;amp; Society 19 (1-2): 45.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="CRASSH"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="inter-disciplinarity"></category></entry></feed>