<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - Judaism</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/judaism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T02:27:48+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Cultures of Belief — post-print version of article</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-post-print-version-of-article.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-10T16:42:23+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T02:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-04-10:/cultures-of-belief-post-print-version-of-article.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As promised, here’s a post-print version of my Cultures of Belief
article, which was published in Anthropological Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/pdf/cultures-of-belief-post-print.pdf" title="Cultures of Belief - post-print pdf"&gt;cultures-of-belief-post-print&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text is identical to the journal version, but the formatting is
different — this is the version I’m allowed to distribute according to
the publishing agreement. If you have …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As promised, here’s a post-print version of my Cultures of Belief
article, which was published in Anthropological Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/pdf/cultures-of-belief-post-print.pdf" title="Cultures of Belief - post-print pdf"&gt;cultures-of-belief-post-print&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The text is identical to the journal version, but the formatting is
different — this is the version I’m allowed to distribute according to
the publishing agreement. If you have access to the journal, for example
through a library, you can see a prettier version &lt;a href="http://ant.sagepub.com/content/12/4/448"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="Evangelicals"></category><category term="gods"></category><category term="Greece"></category><category term="Judaism"></category><category term="Maimonides"></category><category term="Paul Veyne"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry><entry><title>Cultures of Belief – New paper out in Anthropological Theory</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-10T15:31:14+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T02:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-04-10:/cultures-of-belief-new-paper-out-in-anthropological-theory.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just had a new paper out in &lt;a href="http://ant.sagepub.com/content/12/4/448.full.pdf+html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anthropological
Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — this is behind a paywall, I’ll make a post-print
version available through this website soon for those who don’t have
access to the journal through an academic library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is titled ‘Cultures of ignorance’. In a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just had a new paper out in &lt;a href="http://ant.sagepub.com/content/12/4/448.full.pdf+html"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anthropological
Theory&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — this is behind a paywall, I’ll make a post-print
version available through this website soon for those who don’t have
access to the journal through an academic library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper is titled ‘Cultures of ignorance’. In a nutshell, the
argument is that academic students of religion have settled on a way of
accounting for religious language and thought that distinguishes
ordinary, everyday belief from religious belief. The former is
understood to be literal and practical. The latter, by contrast, is
taken to be indirect, metaphorical, symbolic, affective, moral and so
on, and by implication &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be about propositional belief.
Drawing on my own field research in northern China’s Inner Mongolia, I
argue that there are ways of relating to a body of true knowledge that
fit neither of these models. I argue that in order to understand what is
going on in this situation and many others we need to develop an
ethnographic sensibility to locally specific ‘cultures of belief’. To
get this project off to a start, I suggest some initial building blocks
for a general anthropology of belief, based on religious thought in
ancient Greece, mediaeval Judaism, and contemporary US Evangelism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In popular thought about the meaning of religion, as well as
established debates in anthropology, religious belief is interpreted as
either a commitment to a clear set of propositions, or as a non-literal,
symbolic, ethical or social commitment. Anthropologists have tended to
support the latter of these positions, so much so that this can now be
seen as the ‘anthropological’ position; it is also characteristic of the
view of scholars in related disciplines, such as religious studies. This
article argues for a third possibility: that religious (and other)
believers are often engaged in complex, reflexive practices that
stipulate specific cognitive and non-cognitive relationships to
propositional content. This is demonstrated with reference to
contemporary Buddhism in Inner Mongolia, China. The author argues that
the existence of such cultures of belief demonstrates there is a need
for a systematic anthropological theory of belief and suggests some
sources that may contribute to its formulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mair, J., 2013. Cultures of belief. &lt;em&gt;Anthropological Theory&lt;/em&gt;,
12(4), pp.448–466.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="Buddhism"></category><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="Judaism"></category><category term="religion"></category></entry></feed>