<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - neoliberalism</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/neoliberalism.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>‘Neoliberalism’ as ‘conceptual trash heap’</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2015/07/neoliberalism-as-conceptual-trash-heap/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-06T09:31:19+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2015-07-06:/2015/07/neoliberalism-as-conceptual-trash-heap/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post in a long time. Over the last year I moved to
Manchester and started teaching full time. I hope to return to blogging
from time to&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve seen the transcript of the 2012 &lt;a href="../201-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt; debate on the
concept of neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt;, which is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post in a long time. Over the last year I moved to
Manchester and started teaching full time. I hope to return to blogging
from time to&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve seen the transcript of the 2012 &lt;a href="../201-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt; debate on the
concept of neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt;, which is due to be published in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JRAI&lt;/span&gt; next
year. I spoke in the debate as second proposer for the (resoundingly
defeated!) motion &lt;em&gt;The concept of neoliberalism has become an
obstacle to the anthropological understanding of the twenty-first
century&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of an article I came across a few months ago: &lt;a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s12116-009-9040-5"&gt;Boas,
Taylor C., and Jordan Gans-Morse. “Neoliberalism: From new liberal
philosophy to anti-liberal slogan.” &lt;em&gt;Studies in Comparative
International Development&lt;/em&gt; 44.2 (2009): 137-161.&lt;/a&gt; The argument is
similar to the one James Laidlaw and I made in the debate but it is
based on a much more systematic review of social scientific literature
than we were able to present in our short&amp;nbsp;speeches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="page" title="Page 2"&gt;
&lt;div class="section"&gt;
&lt;div class="layoutArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="column"&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a review of 148 articles on neoliberalism published in the top
comparative politics, development, and Latin American studies journals
between 1990 and 2004, we did not find a single article focused on the
definition and usage of neoliberalism, nor are we aware of one published&amp;nbsp;elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the use of neoliberalism in the contemporary study of political
economy differs from that of other normatively charged social science
concepts in three potentially problematic ways. First, its negative
normative valence and connotations of radicalism have produced
asymmetric patterns of use across ideological divides. Second, scholars
who do use the term neoliberalism tend not to define it in empirical
research, even when it is an important independent or dependent
variable. And third, the term is applied to multiple distinct phenomena,
from a set of economic policies or development model to an ideology or
academic paradigm. In present usage, neoliberalism conveys little common
substantive meaning but serves as a clear indicator that one does not
evaluate free markets&amp;nbsp;positively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors make a very interesting argument that the origin of the
term’s contemporary academic usage lies in South American critiques of
Pinochet in the 1970s and 80s. Pinochet was applying radical economic
policies formulated by the ‘Chicago Boys’, based on the thought of Hayek
and&amp;nbsp;Friedman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once established as a common term among Spanish-speaking scholars,
neoliberalism diffused directly into the English-language study of
political economy, such that its present-day usage is heir to the
critical Latin American scholarship of the 1970s and 1980s. In one very
important way, contemporary usage of neoliberalism has changed
fundamentally since that period: it no longer denotes a new form of
liberalism with specific features and empirical referents, but has
become a vague term that can mean virtually anything as long as it
refers to normatively negative phenomena associated with free markets.
As the term neoliberalism has diffused broadly, nothing has prevented
its meaning from drifting even more&amp;nbsp;broadly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This goes some way to explaining the fact that some of the strongest
defenders of the concept of neoliberalism in the discussion part of the
debate were scholars working on Latin&amp;nbsp;America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They also suggest an ingenious explanation of the mechanism by which
the vagueness of ‘neoliberalism’ is established and maintained. They
distinguish contested concepts from contested terms. In the case of
neoliberalism, the concepts are ideas associated with free markets. The
term is the normatively loaded ‘neoliberalism’, which is applied only by
those who are critical of the concepts. Where a term is agreed upon, and
only the underlying concepts are contested, there’s a shared incentive
to police the boundaries of the term.&amp;nbsp;But…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the case of neoliberalism, the conjunction of terminological
contestation and the contested normative valence of the underlying
concepts to which it can refer short circuits debate over the term’s
meaning and proper application. Because the normative valence of free
market phenomena is contested, some scholars have an incentive to
suggest that the negative aspects of markets are more widespread,
whereas others have an incentive to argue that their positive aspects
are more prevalent. Those who use neoliberalism, however, participate in
only one side of this debate. To contest the intension and extension of
neoliberalism, by arguing that certain cases do not qualify or that
certain definitional criteria do not belong, would be to suggest that
the negative aspects of markets are not as widespread as others
maintain—undercutting the still-unresolved argument about whether the
free market is ultimately good or bad. The result is that neoliberalism
has become a conceptual trash heap capable of accommodating multiple
distasteful phenomena without much argument as to whether one or the
other component really&amp;nbsp;belongs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="debate"></category><category term="gdat"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Alastair Macintyre on the moral-instrumental division of the modern world</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2012/12/alastair-macintyre-on-the-moral-instrumental-division-of-the-modern-world/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-15:/2012/12/alastair-macintyre-on-the-moral-instrumental-division-of-the-modern-world/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am reading Alasdair MacIntyre’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0715636405/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0715636405&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=210d14-21"&gt;After
Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1981), and I’ve just come
across a passage that is related to my recent argument about the
problems of the use of the concept of neoliberalism in&amp;nbsp;anthropology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument was that academic advocates …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am reading Alasdair MacIntyre’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/0715636405/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1634&amp;amp;creative=19450&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0715636405&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=210d14-21"&gt;After
Virtue: A Study in Moral Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (1981), and I’ve just come
across a passage that is related to my recent argument about the
problems of the use of the concept of neoliberalism in&amp;nbsp;anthropology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument was that academic advocates of neoliberalism and
academic critics of it share a view of the world, for all their apparent
disagreement, in which all action is &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; moral &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;
instrumental. I argued that this was part of a long argument in western
thought that took the division for granted and in which the problematic
was what the proper balance between the two spheres of life should be,
and that neither position can adequately comprehend forms of moral life
in which effective instrumentality is considered to have intrinsic
ethical&amp;nbsp;value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MacIntyre’s book historicizes this very distinction, attributing its
emergence to the attempt of Enlightenment thinkers to justify morality,
and looks at historical forms of virtue in which the good and the
effective were unified. MacIntyre’s target is not, of course,
‘neoliberalism-ism’, but a theory of morality he describes as emotivism.
He argues that emotivism dominates moral thought in the contemporary&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emotivism, according to Macintyre, is premised on the division of the
social world&amp;nbsp;into,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…a realm of the organizational in which ends are taken to be given
and are not available for rational scrutiny and a realm of the personal
in which judgment and debate about values are central factors, but in
which no rational social resolution of issues is&amp;nbsp;available…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…debates are often staged in terms of a supposed opposition between
individualism and collectivism, each appearing in a variety of doctrinal
forms. On the one side there appear the self-defined protagonists of
individual liberty, on the other the self-defined protagonists of
planning and regulation, of the goods which are available through
bureaucratic organization. But in fact what is crucial is that on which
the contending parties agree, namely that there are only two alternative
modes of social life open to us, one in which the free and arbitrary
choices of individuals are sovereign and one in which the bureaucracy is
sovereign, precisely so it may limit the free and arbitrary choices if
individuals (p.&amp;nbsp;34f).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Alasdair MacIntyre"></category><category term="emotivism"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category></entry><entry><title>Neoliberal is henceforth dead to me</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2012/12/neoliberal-is-henceforth-dead-to-me/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-14T16:53:31+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-14:/2012/12/neoliberal-is-henceforth-dead-to-me/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Theo Kyriakides (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bio_karneia"&gt;@bio_karneia&lt;/a&gt;), who was
present at the &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt; debate on
neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt; for alerting me to a post by Kathleen Fitzpatrick of
Pomona College. She&amp;nbsp;writes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come to despise the term “neoliberal,” to the extent that I’d
really like to see it stricken from academic …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Theo Kyriakides (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bio_karneia"&gt;@bio_karneia&lt;/a&gt;), who was
present at the &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt; debate on
neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt; for alerting me to a post by Kathleen Fitzpatrick of
Pomona College. She&amp;nbsp;writes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come to despise the term “neoliberal,” to the extent that I’d
really like to see it stricken from academic vocabularies everywhere.
It’s less that I have a problem with the actual critique that the term
is meant to levy than with the utterly sloppy and nearly always casually
derisive way in which the term is of late being thrown about. 1
“Neoliberal” is hardly ever used these days to point to instances of the
elevation of market values above all others — it’s used to tar anything
that has anything to do with any market realities&amp;nbsp;whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the rest here: &lt;a href="https://kfitz.info/neoliberal/"&gt;“Neoliberal” | Planned
Obsolescence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="https://kfitz.info/more-on-that-word/"&gt;later post&lt;/a&gt;,
she&amp;nbsp;says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;like “bourgeois” or “reactionary” or any number of other such terms,
I have too often of late heard “neoliberal” deployed as an insult by
people on the left against &lt;em&gt;other people on the left&lt;/em&gt;. It’s the
classic circular firing squad of ideological purity, and it makes me&amp;nbsp;nuts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Kathleen Fitzpatrick"></category><category term="neoliberal university"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category></entry><entry><title>GDAT 2012: Debating “neoliberalism”</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2012/12/gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-05T13:49:55+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-05:/2012/12/gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Saturday I had the pleasure of taking part in &lt;a href="http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/disciplines/socialanthropology/research/gdat/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
an annual debate on anthropological theory hosted by Manchester
University. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt;, the Group for Debates in Anthropological Theory, was
started in the late 80s by Tim Ingold, and has been organized and
chaired more recently by Soumhya Venkatesan. This …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Saturday I had the pleasure of taking part in &lt;a href="http://www.socialsciences.manchester.ac.uk/disciplines/socialanthropology/research/gdat/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;,
an annual debate on anthropological theory hosted by Manchester
University. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt;, the Group for Debates in Anthropological Theory, was
started in the late 80s by Tim Ingold, and has been organized and
chaired more recently by Soumhya Venkatesan. This was the third &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDAT&lt;/span&gt; I
have attended and I think it’s a brilliant institution. People come from
all over the country, and the discussion is always highly engaged and
critical in the best&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year’s motion was: &lt;em&gt;The concept of neoliberalism has become
an obstacle to the anthropological understanding of the twenty-first
century&lt;/em&gt;. James Laidlaw was proposing, I seconded, and Thomas
Hylland Eriksen and Keir Martin&amp;nbsp;opposed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of the concept of ‘neoliberalism’ has been a bugbear of mine
since a conference I attended in 2009. Every panel I attended had at
least one paper on neoliberalism, but each seemed to be talking about
quite different, even contradictory, things — the neoliberal tag seemed
to add nothing. Or worse, it seemed portentously to invoke a whole
global theory as a background explanation without doing the work of
showing how ‘global forces’ are actually linked to or expressed in the
sort of ‘local’ settings the speakers were talking about. It has become
a kind of disciplinary common sense reinforced by a smug sense of shared
moral indignation and that is reason enough to question its&amp;nbsp;usefulness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the speeches will be available on the University of Manchester
website soon, and I understand a recording of the debate will be made
available as a podcast. Eventually, the whole thing, with a
transcription of the questions following the speeches, will be published
in &lt;a href="http://coa.sagepub.com/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critique of
Anthropology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In the meantime, I’ll be happy to send anyone
who’s interested a copy of my speech — here’s a&amp;nbsp;snippet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discourse of academic critics of neoliberalism is nothing but the
discourse of the academic proponents of neoliberalism—but with the signs&amp;nbsp;reversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither side invented the categories it works with. This disagreement
is simply the latest battle in a long, long war in western thought about
the proper balance of the moral and the instrumental spheres of life.
One side in this argument has always argued that the sphere of economic
rationality should be carefully constrained in order to preserve moral
life from its taint. The other side has always argued that more amoral
selfishness in the short term will produce the optimum outcome for all
in the end and is therefore, only apparently paradoxically, the more
moral course of action. What both sides take for granted is the
fundamental division of the moral from the instrumental. (If the concept
of ‘ontology’ were not just as compromised as ‘neoliberalism’, one might
want to deploy it here.) The use of the concept of neoliberalism in
anthropological writing has been little more than an excuse to rehearse
this old and essentially parochial argument, in a way that appears to
mobilize ethnographic evidence but in fact precludes the possibility of
learning anything&amp;nbsp;new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We lost, horribly. I got a good laugh with that line about ‘ontology’
though…talk about professional&amp;nbsp;in-jokes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/span&gt; (31 Jan 2013): The audio recording of the debate is now
available &lt;a href="https://www.podchaser.com/podcasts/talking-anthropology-115090/episodes/ta45-gdat1-neoliberalism-5315861"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="debate"></category><category term="gdat"></category><category term="‘James Laidlaw’"></category><category term="‘Keir Martin’"></category><category term="manchester"></category><category term="neoliberalism"></category><category term="‘Thomas Hylland Eriksen’"></category></entry></feed>