<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - research hierarchy</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/research-hierarchy.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Research Proposal Writing: Understanding the Research Hierarchy</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/how-to-write-research-proposal-social-sciences.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-05-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2024-05-03:/how-to-write-research-proposal-social-sciences.html</id><summary type="html">Writing a research proposal is easy so long as you understand the relationship between research objectives and literature review, research questions, and methods. The research pyramid makes it clear.</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1 id="research-proposal-writing-for-social-sciences-understanding-the-research-pyramid"&gt;Research
Proposal Writing for Social Sciences: Understanding the Research
Pyramid&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-to-write-a-proposal-that-integrates-your-literature-review-research-objective-and-questions-your-methods-and-methodology"&gt;How
to write a proposal that integrates your literature review, research
objective and questions, your methods and methodology?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img alt="The three layers of the research pyramid. Understand the logical relationship and writing your research proposal will be easy." src="https://www.jonathanmair.com/assets/images/research-proposal-pyramid.webp"/&gt;
&lt;figcaption aria-hidden="true"&gt;The three layers of the research pyramid.
Understand the logical relationship and writing your research proposal
will be easy.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years I have been approached countless times by students and
inexperienced researchers with questions about writing a research
proposal for the social sciences. Often they have a draft, but the
elements don’t hang together, the whole thing seems arbitrary, and they
know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice has always been to take a step back from the research
proposal text, and to take time to really understand what I call the
‘Research Hierarchy’, in order to think about how it applies to the
project you are considering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been asked this so many times that I thought it might be useful
to put my answer in writing. I think this may be particularly helpful
because the instructions on how to write research proposals are often
pretty unclear. Understanding the fundamentals and the logic from first
principles will help to produce an effective proposal, whether you’re
applying for a masters or a PhD or for a grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="typical-novice-research-proposals"&gt;Typical novice research
proposals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research proposals are often bad. In order to write a good one, it’s
important to understand what problems commonly occur so that you can
avoid them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Novices often come with a lot of enthusiasm for a particular topic,
some general knowledge about social theory, and research questions that
come out of ‘applying’ the latter to the former. In other words, the
ingredients of a novice research proposal are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passion/insight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attractive/known methods and theories&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research questions determined by (1) and (2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will apply feminist theory to board game culture in order to
understand gender relations among gamers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will analyse Game of Thrones using semiotics in order to
understand the use of symbols in modern television drama.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will use ethnographic methods to study clothing culture among
London Underground commuters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach often results in a research proposal that is
paradoxically &lt;strong&gt;too humble&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;too
ambitious&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By ‘too humble’, I mean that the writers of these kinds of proposals
do not really imagined themselves taking part in a dialogue with
academic research literature. They ‘apply’ theory, but they’re not in
dialogue with it. This is probably OK, but not ideal at undergraduate
level. Beyond that, a research project should realistically expect to
contribute something to the conversation. Even a graduate student
project? Yes absolutely. It’s not as difficult as it sounds, which
brings me to the next point…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…By ‘too ambitious’, I mean that the researcher proposes a topic of
research that is extremely broad. This is likely to result either in a
very superficial treatment, or in an over complex method that may not be
feasible in the time available. The way to avoid this problem is by
narrowing the research objectives down to a manageable size. The best
way to do that is to engage with existing literature and attempt a very
precise, narrow way in which it can be improved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-research-pyramid"&gt;The research pyramid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now we know what to avoid. How do we improve on the novice
research proposal?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key thing is to understand that the elements of a research
proposal—such as research objectives, methods, literature review and so
on—are not there because they’re nice to have. They are related to each
other in a logical and hierarchical manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A research proposal is a pyramid with three layers. You don’t begin
building a pyramid at the top, you build the base first, and the same is
true of a research proposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain, layer by layer…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="the-base-of-the-research-pyramid-research-objectives-and-literature-review"&gt;The
base of the research pyramid: research objectives and literature
review&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The base layer of the research pyramid is made up of Research
Objectives and Literature Review. These are on one level because they
are in a reciprocal relationship. You need to work on them both at the
same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will probably begin with a general research objective. This will
give you an initial orientation to begin your literature search. As you
read, you will be able to think more clearly about your topic. You will
make finer distinctions, and you will find out what people have already
discovered about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, say you want to research prizes and how they work as
incentives. That orients you to the literature, and an initial search
reveals that scholarly work on the topic divides prizes into two major
kinds: &lt;em&gt;ex post&lt;/em&gt; prizes, such as the Nobel Prizes, which award
people for things they have already done, and &lt;em&gt;ex ante&lt;/em&gt; prizes,
which set a challenge beforehand, which people then respond to, in order
to be judged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you know that to make a contribution to the literature you will
probably need to focus on one or the other, or perhaps interrogate that
distinction itself. Otherwise your efforts will be begging the most
basic question of prize studies!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So your research objectives will narrow and you will have a more
focused orientation to the literature. You will learn more, and you will
probably want to narrow your focus again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This iterative process should continue until you’re happy that you
have a focus that corresponds closely to the literature, but that is
narrow enough that it will be easy for you to carry out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="the-second-layer-of-the-research-pyramid-research-questions"&gt;The
second layer of the research pyramid: research questions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your research objective sets out the general issues you want to
understand. How long will it take you to answer them? How long is a
piece of string?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you stay at the general level, it is impossible to guage whether a
proposed research project is feasible in the time and with the resources
available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is why you move from your general research objectives to
specific research questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A research question should be specific enough to be able to say
definitively whether you have answered it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a research objective might be to understand how
intensely young people in Spain use social media apps. That’s a good
research objective, but it will be hard to know whether we have
definitively answered it or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A corresponding research question might be: In Spain’s biggest 4
cities, what proportion of people between 13 and 26 use social media
apps for more than four hours a day. This is concrete question with a
concrete answer. We will know when we have answered it and we can have a
good guess about the resources needed to come to an answer. The same is
no true of the research objective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are likely to have a range of specific research questions such as
this. The number and variety will depend on the resources at your
disposal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="the-pinnacle-methods-and-methodology"&gt;The pinnacle: methods and
methodology&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve identified the research questions that will help you to fulfil
your research objectives and contribute to the debates you have
identified in your literature review. Finally, it’s time to select your
methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s right that you’re doing this last. Methods are a tool for
answering questions. It doesn’t make sense to select your methods first
and then find some questions to apply them to. That would be like
selecting a tool and then deciding what home repairs to do, rather than
deciding on a problem that needs fixing (objective), deciding how to fix
it (research questions), and then looking for the right tool for the
job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(OK, there are important exceptions to this rule!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Methods are the important bit here: what you will do, when and where.
Methodology is the part that explains why these methods are suitable
ways of going about answering your research questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="to-summarise"&gt;To summarise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research pyramid is a way to build a research proposal in three
logically linked steps, building from foundation to pinnacle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol type="1"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research objectives &amp;lt;–&amp;gt; Literature review: a reciprocal
process in which you refine your thinking about a topic and identify a
narrow aspect of the topic to which your research will contribute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research questions: specify the general research objectives in terms
of &lt;em&gt;answerable questions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Methodology/Methods: appropriate for the specific research
questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="social science research methods"></category><category term="research proposal"></category><category term="research methods"></category><category term="methodology"></category><category term="social science research"></category><category term="research hierarchy"></category></entry></feed>