<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - self-cultivation</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/self-cultivation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T09:52:56+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Cross-cultural conversations at cross-purposes</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2012/12/cross-cultural-conversations-at-cross-purposes/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-12-05T19:13:32+01:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T09:52:56+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-12-05:/2012/12/cross-cultural-conversations-at-cross-purposes/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument in the recent &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;neoliberalism
debate&lt;/a&gt; was that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;evidence of discontent about any aspect, be it ever so narrow, of
what have been identified as neoliberal transformations is taken,
without further justification, as a rejection of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the
phenomena that have been so identified&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part of my argument in the recent &lt;a href="../2012-12-05-gdat-neoliberalism-anthropology"&gt;neoliberalism
debate&lt;/a&gt; was that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;evidence of discontent about any aspect, be it ever so narrow, of
what have been identified as neoliberal transformations is taken,
without further justification, as a rejection of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of the
phenomena that have been so identified&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point was that just because lots of people in different countries
are critics of, say, structural adjustment programmes, we cannot leap to
the conclusion that they share the same conception of the state and
civil society and all agree on the proper balance of power and resources
between the two; their motivations and assumptions might be quite
different in each case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a formal problem of cross-cultural description or comparison:
the conversation at cross-purposes. We recognize something familiar in
other people’s statements, and rush to fill in the rest from our own
common-sense ideas, which may be quite different. My favourite example
of this is one that operates in both directions — a reciprocal
conversation at cross-purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="self-cultivation-jesus-christ-and-christ-jesus"&gt;Self-Cultivation,
Jesus Christ, and Christ Jesus&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christian missionaries, mainly Americans, operate in China in spite
of a prohibition on missionary activity. Their message tends to be the
&lt;strong&gt;rules-based&lt;/strong&gt; version of modern Evangelism that has taken
so much of the world by storm over the past 30 years: don’t drink, don’t
smoke, don’t gamble, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christians I have met in villages in the north of China, or people
who were &lt;em&gt;interested in Christianity&lt;/em&gt; as they would invariably
put it, were, it seemed to me, used to thinking about religious practice
quite differently: as being aimed at a gradual process of
&lt;strong&gt;self-cultivation&lt;/strong&gt;. Like an impressive athletic feat —
such as running a marathon — this is something that is easy for anyone
to admire. But to participate — that takes a certain degree of
commitment, free time and self-confidence. Again and again, when I asked
people if they were Christian they would self-deprecatingly say that
they knew little about it, that they were busy, but planned to start
being a Christian in the future, perhaps when the harvest was in and
there was less farm work to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in China researching the revival of Buddhism in Mongolian
areas, and Buddhists — or people who were interested in Buddhism — would
often tell me similar things: Buddhism is a deep culture that is very
powerful, but not many people are capable of putting it into practice,
they were happy being relatively passive admirers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the village Christians do practise, they see the purpose of
self-denial not as the fulfilment of an imperative duty, but rather as a
technology through which they will gain good fortune through hard work.
This means that it the practices taught by missionaries, sometimes long
ago, tend to drift into more extreme forms of asceticism. For instance,
in one village I was told that a religion of Christ Jesus had emerged to
challenge the established religion of Jesus Christ. The followers of
Christ Jesus interpreted the injunction to pray often as an esoteric
teaching involving sitting absolutely still for hours with a wet towel
on one’s head— a dangerous as well as an uncomfortable proposition in
windy, icy Inner Mongolia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="guilty-buddhists"&gt;Guilty Buddhists&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reciprocal part of this conversation at cross-purposes is the
adoption of Buddhism in many non-Asian contexts in which religion,
especially monotheisms, tends to be thought of as a revelation of moral
duty — that is, as part of a system of &lt;strong&gt;rule-based
morality&lt;/strong&gt; — rather than a set of technologies for
self-development. The corollary of duty is guilt. If what I have read is
representative, Western Buddhist leaders seem to be occupied quite a lot
of the time with advising their followers not to feel guilty if they
miss out on a meditation session (just google &lt;a href="https://www.google.co.uk/search?q=don't+feel+guilty+for+not+meditating"&gt;‘don’t
feel guilty for not meditating’&lt;/a&gt; to see what I mean), or if they
cannot resist eating meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This conversation at cross-purposes is facilitated by near-enough
‘religion’ concepts — false friends that make communication easy, even
intuitive. The confusion that arises is evident in the accusations of
hypocrisy, or justifications of apparent hypocrisy, that arose in early
anthropological studies of Buddhism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea that a Buddhist who does not follow Buddhist precepts is
hypocritical, among my Inner Mongolian Buddhist friends at least, would
be as inappropriate as accusing a Manchester United fan of being
hypocritical for failing to play in the Premier League. On the other
side, to my Chinese and Mongolian informants, foreign religionists —
mainly those missionaries — often seem arrogant because they imagine
that they themselves are capable right now, without any preparation, let
alone indefinite deferment, of participating in all the practices that
are commanded of them by their God. (I’m not making a point about
Chinese people getting Christianity wrong, or non-Asians getting
Buddhism wrong — I don’t have a horse in those races, I’m just
interested in the formal problem.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-request"&gt;A request&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some time I have been toying with the idea of compiling a
compendium of cross-cultural conversations at cross-purposes, or
cross-cultural faux amis / &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_friend"&gt;false friends&lt;/a&gt;. It
would include those situations in which concepts on each side of the
conversation are different enough to produce disagreements or confusion,
but similar enough that it may be unclear where the disagreement
originates. Please let me know in the comments or by email if you know
of any good examples for my collection.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="Buddhism"></category><category term="China"></category><category term="Christianity"></category><category term="conversations at cross-purposes"></category><category term="ethics"></category><category term="Inner Mongolia"></category><category term="missionaries"></category><category term="self-cultivation"></category></entry></feed>