<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - social science</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/social-science.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Evolution and Religion Part II</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2012-11-18-evolution-and-religion-part-ii/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-11-18T11:15:40+01:00</published><updated>2023-06-14T08:32:30+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2012-11-18:/2012-11-18-evolution-and-religion-part-ii/</id><summary type="html">&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 220px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Robertson_Smith"&gt;&lt;img alt="William Robertson Smith" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/WilliamRobertsonSmith.jpg" title="William Robertson Smith"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
William Robertson Smith (source: Wikipedia)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a reply to &lt;del&gt;Martin&lt;/del&gt; Michael Blume’s &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/#comment-18"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt;
to my previous &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, which
was itself was a comment on his blog on &lt;a href="http://www.scilogs.com/nature-of-faith/its-about-fertility-stupid-the-evolutionary-adaptivity-of-religion/"&gt;www.scilogs.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;del&gt;
Martin
&lt;/del&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael — Thanks for the links (reproduced below) and for engaging
with my&amp;nbsp;comment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read those …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;figure class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 220px"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Robertson_Smith"&gt;&lt;img alt="William Robertson Smith" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/63/WilliamRobertsonSmith.jpg" title="William Robertson Smith"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption class="wp-caption-text"&gt;
William Robertson Smith (source: Wikipedia)
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a reply to &lt;del&gt;Martin&lt;/del&gt; Michael Blume’s &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/#comment-18"&gt;comment&lt;/a&gt;
to my previous &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion/"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;, which
was itself was a comment on his blog on &lt;a href="http://www.scilogs.com/nature-of-faith/its-about-fertility-stupid-the-evolutionary-adaptivity-of-religion/"&gt;www.scilogs.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;del&gt;
Martin
&lt;/del&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Michael — Thanks for the links (reproduced below) and for engaging
with my&amp;nbsp;comment!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read those two papers now –they are thought provoking and
contain some great lines (“evolutionary theorists brought up far more
scientific arguments — but committed believers in supernatural agents
brought up far more children”–love it!), but I don’t think they really
answer my initial&amp;nbsp;objection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On page 118 of the Reproductive Benefits paper, you write (I’ve added
emphasis and labels in square&amp;nbsp;brackets):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;” [1] Religiosity, understood as *believing* in supernatural guidance
and surveillance of all parties involved, evolved (and evolves) as a
biological and highly successful solution. [2] Humans who are *members*
of religious communities show statistically higher motivations towards
marriage, children and family values, more cooperative orientation and
finally higher reproductive success than their secular&amp;nbsp;contemporaries”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I am questioning is the relation between religiosity as defined
in [1] and the membership of religious communities referred to in [2].
You draw conclusions about ‘religiosity’ (i.e., belief, on your
definition — I’ll use this word with that force from now on) on the
basis of data about religious affiliation, taking the latter to be
indicative of the former. It is clear from the social scientific
literature on religion that the link between these things is uncertain
to say the&amp;nbsp;least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this in any way invalidates your observations about religious
&lt;em&gt;communities&lt;/em&gt; and reproduction. But if I am right the following
objections&amp;nbsp;follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="over-interpretation-of-the-data"&gt;1. Over-interpretation of the&amp;nbsp;data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be over-interpreting the census data in making the leap from
affiliation to traditional communities with religious associations to
religiosity, on your terms. (I am dubious about the methodology of the
World Values Survey for many of the same reasons by the way, but it’s a
long time since I’ve looked at it so I can’t comment in&amp;nbsp;detail.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gave Day’s study as an example in my post because her work directly
addresses the difference between people’s ‘superempirical’ behaviour and
thought and their response to questions about religious affiliation in a
national&amp;nbsp;census.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the question of the discrepancy between belief and
affiliation has been a constant theme in social scientific studies of
religion since at least the end of the 19C and the work of William
Robertson Smith (ref&amp;nbsp;below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason this question is of enduring interest is that it confounds
the expectations of modern models of religion that are basically
Protestant or post-reformation in nature, especially the expectation
that religion is above all about a personal, interior relationship to
God and the holy, that a particular tradition of worship is associated
with particular institutions and so on. Even in countries (such as the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;) where this model might be expected to apply most strongly (because
for centuries it has been a model of what religion &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be
like), ethnographic work (such as Day’s) shows consistently that the
boundaries between beliefs and boundaries between religious affiliation
are frequently do not line up in the way the model would&amp;nbsp;predict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="anachronism"&gt;2.&amp;nbsp;Anachronism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it were shown that the association between religious
affiliation and religious belief were sound for modern populations, your
conclusions project this combination back throughout history and
prehistory. If we didn’t know anything about changing configurations of
religious behaviour, then that might be a reasonable move. However,
there’s plenty of evidence that the idea of a discrete religion that
comprises a combination of {(i) an exclusive, systematic religious
doctrine + (ii) exclusive use of certain religious practices + (iii) a
specific and exclusive religious affiliation} is a relatively recent
invention that is even now by no means the norm, and which requires a
great deal of policing to make sure that people defined by any one of
these characteristics are also defined by the other&amp;nbsp;two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you have evidence that contradicts the consensus in the
literature, then explaining the evolutionary origins and persistence of
religiosity throughout human existence in terms of the reproductive
advantage it bestows on religious communities may be like seeking the
explanation for the origins and persistence of language over 100s of
thousands of years in terms of its essential role in hip hop. Doing this
would not only misrepresent the nature of language over the long term,
it would also make hip-hop seem like a universal and transhistorical&amp;nbsp;phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By eliding the difference between religious affiliation and religious
belief, and drawing the conclusion that the combination is an
evolutionary adaptation, you give the impression that religion in this
sense is universal and&amp;nbsp;transhistorical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t, by the way, have any axe to grind (some social scientists
do) whatsoever on the question of human universals — I think it’s
obvious that there is such a thing as human nature and that we ought to
try to understand it, but it’s important that in doing that we do take
into account everything we know about human&amp;nbsp;variation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More to come!…&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;a href="http://jonathanmair.com/evolution-and-religion-part-iii/" title="Evolution and Religion Part III"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/span&gt; 5 Dec 2012: Don’t know anything about the quality/provenance
of this research, but if it’s right it’s grist to my mill: &lt;a href="http://www.religiondispatches.org/dispatches/guest_bloggers/6648/%E2%80%98nones%E2%80%99_&amp;amp;ne%3b_nonreligious_%7c_/"&gt;‘Nones’
≠&amp;nbsp;Nonreligious&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="text-decoration: underline;"&gt;References&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was the first major work to question the link between belief
and communal&amp;nbsp;affiliation:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smith, William Robertson. 1889. &lt;em&gt;Lectures on the Religion of the
Semites&lt;/em&gt;. Edinburgh: Adam and Charles&amp;nbsp;Black.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These articles by Talal Asad criticise the tendency of other
scholars of religion to assume that personal, internal psychological
experience, such as belief, is central to religion, thus universalizing
certain aspects of contemporary Christian&amp;nbsp;experience:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asad, Talal. 1983. “Anthropological Conceptions of Religion:
Reflections on Geertz.” &lt;em&gt;Man: The Journal of the Royal
Anthropological Institute&lt;/em&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NS&lt;/span&gt; 18:&amp;nbsp;237–259.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asad, T. 2001. “Reading a modern classic: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;W. C.&lt;/span&gt; Smith’s The Meaning
and End of Religion.” &lt;em&gt;History of Religions&lt;/em&gt; 40 (3):&amp;nbsp;205–222.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This book describes the process through which leaders of the
newly named ‘World Religions’ remade their traditions in the image of
post-Reformation Christianity in the&amp;nbsp;19C:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Masuzawa, Tomoko. 2005. &lt;em&gt;The Invention of World Religions : or,
How European Universalism Was Preserved in the Language of
Pluralism&lt;/em&gt;. Chicago, Ill.: London : University of Chicago&amp;nbsp;Press.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article describes a similar process in the Russian Reupblic
of Altai, where Protestant missionaries failed to garner many converts
to Christianity, but succeeded in spreading the idea of exclusive
religiosity, in a situation in which people had previously been
religiously&amp;nbsp;promiscuous:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Broz, Ludek. 2009. &lt;a href="http://www.academia.edu/1035385/CONVERSION_TO_RELIGION_NEGOTIATING_CONTINUITY_AND_DISCONTINUITY_IN_CONTEMPORARY_ALTAI"&gt;“Conversion
to Religion?”&lt;/a&gt; In &lt;em&gt;Conversion After Socialism: Disruptions,
Modernisms and Technologies of Faith in the Former Soviet Union&lt;/em&gt;,
ed. Mathijs Pelkmans. Berghahn&amp;nbsp;Books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article has a good review of the ethnographic literature on
belief, much of which is concerned with explaining the common
discrepancy between religious affiliation, religious practice and
religious&amp;nbsp;belief:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lindquist, Galina, and Simon Coleman. 2008. “Introduction: Against
Belief?” &lt;em&gt;Social Analysis&lt;/em&gt; 52&amp;nbsp;(1).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On the dangers of drawing universal conclusions about human
nature that inadvertently incorporate specific characteristics of those
populations for which data is easy to come&amp;nbsp;by:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heine, Stephen, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://cmbconference2012.org/the-weirdest-people-in-the-world-the-inductive-challenge-for-psychology/"&gt;The
weirdest people in the world: The inductive challenge for
psychology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (conference&amp;nbsp;abstract)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="belief"></category><category term="evolution"></category><category term="Michael Blume"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="social science"></category><category term="Talal Asad"></category><category term="William Robertson Smith"></category></entry></feed>