<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jonathan Mair - virtue ethics</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/feeds/tag/virtue-ethics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.jonathanmair.com/</id><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><subtitle>Out of the frying pan.</subtitle><entry><title>Literacy, religious renaissance and the 'morality system'</title><link href="https://www.jonathanmair.com/2013/04/literacy-religious-renaissance-and-the-morality-system/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-04-04T20:00:23+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T08:27:48+02:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Mair</name></author><id>tag:www.jonathanmair.com,2013-04-04:/2013/04/literacy-religious-renaissance-and-the-morality-system/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-post from ethics.CRASSH.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="felicitas-becker-on-islamic-reformism-and-sufi-traditionalism-in-tanzania"&gt;Felicitas
Becker on Islamic reformism and Sufi traditionalism in Tanzania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve just read two fascinating papers by &lt;a href="http://www.hist.cam.ac.uk/directory/fmb26@cam.ac.uk"&gt;Felicitas
Becker&lt;/a&gt; on moral conflict in East Africa. Both papers describe the
relationship between Islamist reformers and Sufi-influenced
traditionalists in rural Tanzania. Broadly speaking, the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a cross-post from ethics.CRASSH.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="felicitas-becker-on-islamic-reformism-and-sufi-traditionalism-in-tanzania"&gt;Felicitas
Becker on Islamic reformism and Sufi traditionalism in Tanzania&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve just read two fascinating papers by &lt;a href="http://www.hist.cam.ac.uk/directory/fmb26@cam.ac.uk"&gt;Felicitas
Becker&lt;/a&gt; on moral conflict in East Africa. Both papers describe the
relationship between Islamist reformers and Sufi-influenced
traditionalists in rural Tanzania. Broadly speaking, the Islamists are
young, have international connections (though these are limited), and
their leaders claim legitimacy as a result of their scriptural
scholarship. The traditionalists are drawn from the older generations
and derive their authority from their descent from founders of local
mosques, or from their place in a chain of transmission of oral
knowledge. Most local people, Becker notes, consider themselves Muslims,
but observe the debates between the two groups without feeling the need
to declare themselves partisans of either side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the papers, ‘Islamic Reform and Historical Change in the Care
of the Dead’ (2009) focuses on disagreements between the two parties
around funerary practices, which take on great importance in this
context. Traditionalists have elaborate funerals in which prayers and
the Quran are recited over the funeral procession and the deceased is
read instructions on how to meet the angels after the burial is
complete. To the elders who represent this tradition, these measures
show that they are more punctilious in caring for the dead than their
nomadic forebears who, before the adoption of Islamic usages, would
abandon settlements along with the corpses of the dead. To the
reformists, the intercessions on behalf of, and interaction with, the
deceased are accretions that are not justified by Quran or Hadith and
must therefore be relinquished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other paper, ‘Rural Islamism during the “War on Terror”‘ (2006)
considers a wider range of disagreements over practice, and also
addresses the question of how far the reformers, who are nicknamed by
other ‘Al Qaeda’, are in fact part of a coherent ‘international terror’
movement. Becker’s admirably nuanced conclusion, if I understand it
correctly, is that although they are politically activist in theory, and
in a way that could potentially lead to violent conflict, the political
plank of their programme finds no traction with local concerns and is
therefore barely a live part of their practice, while the international
connections are tenuous. Meanwhile, the other aspect of their programme,
the claim that scriptural scholarship is the sole source of religious
legitimacy has found great support among the population, and even
grudging assent among those who find themselves on the opposite side of
debates about specific practices. This aspect of Becker’s material makes
it interesting in terms of the CRASSH Speaking Ethically Across Borders
Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-morality-system-and-literacy"&gt;The ‘morality system’ and
literacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 2006 paper, Becker notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…the opinions expounded by &lt;em&gt;Ansaar&lt;/em&gt; [the reformists/Islamists]
consistently tend towards the imposition of stricter rules. They are
more concerned than others about the loss of ritual purity through
contact with the opposite sex; they support a ban on alcohol and have
suggested that smoking, too, is &lt;em&gt;haram&lt;/em&gt;, religiously prohibited.
… They have also introduced new forms of veiling to Rwangwa, have
changed standards for &lt;em&gt;halal&lt;/em&gt; (religiously correct) slaughter and
have questioned the acceptability of established ways of dealing with
witchcraft. (Becker 2006: 594)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me think about the relation of literacy and forms of
ethics. Much recent anthropological work on ethics has taken on a
distinction from philosophy between virtue ethics and what Bernard
Williams calls the ‘morality system’. The morality system is about
judgment of acts against legalistic codes of behaviour, lists of
obligations and taboos, and it leads to a concern with the refinement of
rules for particular circumstances, and with moral dilemmas. Virtue
ethics is about the judgment of character against models of excellence,
and leads to a concern with the identification of exemplars, and with
pedagogical techniques that lead to the cultivation of particular
virtues (including what Foucault calls ‘techniques of the self’).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of anthropological work on Islamic reformists has emphasised
the way in which their reforms are connected to virtue ethical
programmes of character development, but I wonder if there’s a general
relationship between reformist movements that base legitimacy on
scriptural sources and the importance of the ‘morality system’.
Character-based ethics requires a good deal of interpretation in order
to work out how an exemplar would act in the current situation (see
Humphrey 1997 on this). Virtues that are partly or mainly about embodied
dispositions are apt to be expressed in imagistic forms that
underdetermine their expression (Carrithers 1990). Is it difficult to
combine this interpretative flexibility and the autonomy it implies with
an insistence on submission to scripture as a sole source of
authority?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Becker’s Tanzanian case study, the traditionalist elders apply
this kind of reasoning to the conduct of funerals. The reformists argue
from scripture that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Prophet, peace be upon him, prohibits the corpse [to be sung to],
that is to say, when we get up to go to the graveyard to bury someone,
we are required to be quiet and to ponder that our fellow Muslim has
died and we will die too. Therefore we must be quiet. And the Prophet
says don’t follow the hearse with any sort of noise, let people be quiet
and reflect. (Becker 2006: 592)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sufis’ riposte is that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the days of the prophet, the graves were situated very close to
the houses of the liv- ing. But our graves are far from our villages.
Moreover, our faith is not as strong as that of the first Muslims. Were
we to go to the graveyard in silence, our thoughts might start to wander
and some might start to discuss, say, football on the way to the grave!
So our elders decided we had better recite the shahada on the way to the
grave, to keep our minds focused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This could, I think, be interpreted as a more character-based
approach to ethics. Though the traditionalists accept the idea that
scripture, and not established custom, is the proper arbiter of
practice, they maintain enough autonomy from it to interpret it in the
light of specific local and personal conditions. Perhaps this shows that
they are more concerned with emulating the underlying character
expressed by the Prophet’s actions, something that can never be entirely
captured in words, because it is always contextual, rather than
reproducing the actions, which can be more precisely described in the
text, themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to reach a conclusion on this question on the basis of
this material alone, but perhaps a comparative approach would turn up a
regular association between text-based revival movements
(i.e. renaissances — Goody 2009), and a shift away from a concern with
character and towards a concern with moral rules. Or the shift might be
away from a complex character approach, with multiple, perhaps mutually
incompatible, virtues or exemplars available to the moral subject,
towards a simpler character approach which focuses all effort on the
single virtue of perfect submission to the authority of the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Main texts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becker, F., 2006. Rural Islamism during the “war on terror”: A
Tanzanian case study. &lt;em&gt;African Affairs&lt;/em&gt;, 105(421),
pp.583–603.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becker, F., 2011. Islamic Reform and Historical Change in the Care of
the Dead: Conflicts Over Funerary Practice Among Tanzanian Muslims.
&lt;em&gt;Africa&lt;/em&gt;, 79(03), pp.416–434.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further reading&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carrithers, M., 1990. Jainism and Buddhism as enduring historical
streams. &lt;em&gt;JASO (Journal of the Anthropological Society of
Oxford)&lt;/em&gt;, 21(2), pp.141–163.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faubion, J.D., 2001. Toward an Anthropology of Ethics: Foucault and
the Pedagogies of Autopoiesis. &lt;em&gt;Representations&lt;/em&gt;, (74),
pp.83–104. Available at:
http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.1525/rep.2001.74.1.83.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foucault, M., 1990. &lt;em&gt;The history of sexuality volume 3: the care
of the self&lt;/em&gt;, London: Penguin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goody, J., 2009. &lt;em&gt;Renaissances&lt;/em&gt;, Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humphrey, C. 1997. Exemplars and rules: aspects of the discourse of
moralities in Mongolia. In Howell, S. (ed). &lt;em&gt;The ethnography of
moralities&lt;/em&gt;. London: Routledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Laidlaw, J., 2002. For An Anthropology Of Ethics And Freedom.
&lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute&lt;/em&gt;, 8(2),
pp.311–332.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Williams, B.A.O., 1985. &lt;em&gt;Ethics and the limits of philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,
Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="anthropology"></category><category term="anthropology of ethics"></category><category term="religion"></category><category term="Felicitas Becker"></category><category term="funerary practice"></category><category term="Islam"></category><category term="Islamism"></category><category term="morality system"></category><category term="Sufism"></category><category term="Tanzania"></category><category term="virtue ethics"></category></entry></feed>